<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Biochem</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Biochemistry</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2091</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">60996</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2091-2-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2091-2-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reconstitution of licensed replication origins on <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei using purified proteins</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>Peter J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>peter.gillespie@cshl.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Anatoliy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>a.li@dundee.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>J Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>j.j.blow@dundee.ac.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>CRC Chromosome Replication Research Group, Wellcome Trust Biocentre, University of Dundee, Dundee DD1 5EH, UK</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Current address: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 1 Bungtown Road, Cold Spring Harbor, New York 11724, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2001</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2091/2/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2001</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2001 Gillespie et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gillespie et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>In order to ensure precise chromosome duplication, eukaryotes "license" their replication origins during late mitosis and early G1 by assembling complexes of Mcm2-7 onto them. Mcm2-7 are essential for DNA replication, but are displaced from origins as they initiate, thus ensuring that no origin fires more than once in a single cell cycle.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Here we show that a combination of purified nucleoplasmin, the origin recognition complex (ORC), Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7 can promote functional origin licensing and the assembly of Mcm2-7 onto <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei. The reconstituted reaction is inhibited by geminin, a specific RLF-B/Cdt1 inhibitor. Interestingly, the purified ORC used in the reconstitution had apparently lost the Orc6 subunit, suggesting that Orc6 is not essential for replication licensing. We use the reconstituted system to make a preliminary analysis of the different events occuring during origin assembly, and examine their nucleotide requirements. We show that the loading of <italic>Xenopus</italic> ORC onto chromatin is strongly stimulated by both ADP, ATP and ATP-&#x003b3;-S whilst the loading of Cdc6 and Cdt1 is stimulated only by ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7 are the only proteins required for functional licensing and the loading of Mcm2-7 onto chromatin. The requirement for nucleoplasmin probably only reflects a requirement to decondense sperm chromatin before ORC can bind to it. Use of this reconstituted system should allow a full biochemical analysis of origin licensing and Mcm2-7 loading.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>During S phase of the eukaryotic cell division cycle the entire genome must be faithfully duplicated. The many thousands of replication forks involved in this process must be co-ordinated to ensure that, despite the very large quantities of DNA involved, no section of DNA is left unreplicated and no section of DNA is replicated more than once. Cells achieve this by dividing the process of replication origin activation into two distinct phases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. During late mitosis and early G1, proteins are assembled onto replication origins which culminates in the origin becoming 'licensed' for a single round of DNA replication by loading complexes of Mcm2-7 proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In yeast, a 'pre-replicative complex' (pre-RC) forms a footprint over replication origins during G1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] which may well correspond to the Mcm2-7 loading that represents the licensed state, although it is possible that other factors in addition to those required for origin licensing are involved. During S phase, replication forks are initiated at licensed replication origins / pre-RCs following activation of the Cdc7 kinase and S phase cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs). Mcm2-7 are displaced from the origin as initiation occurs, thereby ensuring that each origin fires no more than once in each cell cycle. Following displacement from origins, Mcm2-7 appear to move along with the replication fork [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], consistent with their providing essential helicase activity for the progression of the replication fork [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>Three other proteins are known to be required for licensing replication origins and loading of Mcm2-7 onto them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]: the Origin Recognition Complex (ORC), Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. ORC is first required on the DNA in order to recruit Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1. The continued presence of ORC, Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 are not required for Mcm2-7 to remain bound to DNA once licensing has occurred [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. By restricting the activity of ORC, Cdc6 or RLF-B/Cdt1 to a period between late mitosis and the end of G1, the relicensing of replicated origins can therefore be prevented. At least two activities present at other periods of the cell cycle, geminin (an RLF-B/Cdt1 inhibitor) and CDKs, are known to inhibit origin licensing and pre-RC assembly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>In order to understand how origin licensing and Mcm2-7 loading are regulated, we have been purifying from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts all the proteins required to support functional origin licensing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. We chose <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei as the DNA template because it is the natural substrate for replication in <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs and because it is replicated very efficiently in the cell-free system. Using this assay we have previously shown that the licensing of <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei requires ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. We have also shown that this process requires nucleoplasmin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], which is needed to remove the sperm basic proteins from sperm nuclei and decondense the chromatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], which in turn is required for ORC to bind to the chromatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>In the present report we show that a combination of these purified proteins (nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7) can efficiently license <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei and assemble Mcm2-7 onto it. We show that the reconstituted reaction is dependent on ATP and is inhibited by geminin. We use the reconstituted system to make a preliminary analysis of the different events occuring during the licensing of replication origins.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characterization of protein fractions</title><p>We have been performing a systematic fractionation of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts to identify all the proteins required to reconstitute functionally licensed replication origins on <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The sequential separation of activities present in whole egg extract is summarised in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Preliminary reconstitution experiments suggested that a combination of nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1, and Mcm2-7 were sufficient to support efficient origin licensing of <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei (PJG, data not shown). During the fractionation, no additional activities that stimulate origin licensing were observed [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and data not shown]. In addition to this scheme, we also prepared three of the proteins (nucleoplasmin, Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1) by different means. Nucleoplasmin was purified by a different published protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], recombinant Cdc6 was prepared from baculovirus-infected insect cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and recombinant RLF-B/Cdt1 was prepared from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Fractionation scheme for proteins used in this study. Interphase Xenopus egg extract was fractionated by the methods outlined. See Materials and Methods for more details. Cdc6 was not purified to homogeneity but was replaced in the reconstituted reaction with recombinant material produced in insect cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-1"/></fig><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows Coomassie gels of the purified proteins. Purified nucleoplasmin showed a number of different bands that correspond to different phosphorylated forms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). Purified ORC yielded 5 specific bands, corresponding to XOrc1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). No band corresponding to XOrc6 was observed, and to date no <italic>Xenopus ORC6</italic> gene has been cloned. ORC purified from HeLa cell chromatin has also been reported to lack Orc6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], and in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Orc6 is not required for ORC to bind origin DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. We also observed two additional proteins that contaminate the <italic>Xenopus</italic> ORC preparation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. These proteins were subjected to MALDI-TOF analysis and were identified as <italic>Xenopus</italic> Klp1 and Kcm1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The chromatographic behaviour of these proteins suggests that they do not form complexes with ORC [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and data not shown]. Further, immunodepletion of ORC from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts did not co-deplete XKlp1 (data not shown). We therefore conclude that Klp1 and Kcm1 are fortuitous contaminants of our ORC preparation. Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> Cdc6 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], purified RLF-B/Cdt1 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2d</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and recombinant &#x00394;Cdt1 (amino acids 141&#x02013;621 of Xenopus Cdt1, Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] showed a single band of the expected molecular weight. Complexes of <italic>Xenopus</italic> Mcm(2+4+6+7) and Mcm(3+5) were purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2f</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2g</xref>). The Mcm(3+5) contained two contaminating bands of ~52 and ~58 kDa, which we were unable to identify by mass spectrometry. However, their chromatographic behaviour suggests that they are not components of the Mcm2-7 complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Recombinant geminin was prepared from <italic>E. coli</italic> as described (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2h</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Purified proteins used in this study. Purified proteins were run on SDS polyacrylamide gels, and visualized with either Coomassie Blue (a-c, e-h) or silver staining (d). <bold>a,</bold> Nucleoplasmin purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. <bold>b,</bold> ORC purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. <bold>c,</bold> Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> Cdc6 purified from baculovirus-infected insect cells. <bold>d,</bold> RLF-B/Cdt1 purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. <bold>e,</bold> Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> &#x00394;Cdt1 purified from <italic>E. coli.</italic><bold>f,</bold> Mcm(2+4+6+7) purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. <bold>g,</bold> Mcm(3+5) purified from <italic>Xenopus</italic> eggs. <bold>h,</bold> Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> geminin purified from <italic>E. coll.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Specific assays for individual proteins</title><p>In order to minimise the risk that any of these fractions were contaminated with other activities required for origin licensing, we wanted to ensure that each of them was used in the reconstitution at limiting quantities. We therefore titrated each of the purified fractions into a separate assay that was specific for each activity (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Nucleoplasmin reached an optimum at ~4 ng / ng template DNA for both a crude licensing reaction (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>) and sperm decondensation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. This is approximately equal to 1 nucleoplasmin pentamer for each 64 bp DNA, close to the expected density of protamines on sperm DNA and consistent with the role of nucleoplasmin being to decondense the chromatin by removal of protamines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Activity of the purified proteins. Different quantities of purified proteins were subjected to specific individual assays, using <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei as substrate. Protein quantity is given as mass of protein per ng template DNA (a-f) or mass of protein per &#x003bc;l extract (g). DNA synthesis is expressed as % of the DNA template replicated (a-f), or ng DNA synthesised per &#x003bc;l extract (g). <bold>a,</bold> Nucleoplasmin activity required in a crude licensing assay. <bold>b,</bold> ORC activity required for licensing in an ORC-depleted extract. <bold>c,</bold> Cdc6 activity required for licensing in an Cdc6-depleted extract. <bold>d, e,</bold> RLF-B activity required in a crude licensing assay. <bold>f,</bold> RLF-M/Mcm2-7 activity required in an Mcm2-7-depleted extract. <bold>g,</bold> Replication inhibition by geminin in whole egg extract containing 3 ng/&#x003bc;l DNA. Arrows show the protein quantity used in subsequent reconstitution experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-3"/></fig><p>ORC was assayed by titrating into an extract previously immunodepleted with anti-Orc1 antibodies, an assay specific for licensing activities co-depleted with ORC (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>). Purified ORC reached an optimum at ~85 pg / ng DNA, equal to one molecule of ORC per ~6 kb template DNA. This is close to the expected density of ORC on <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm chromatin in the early embryo (~1 ORC per 10&#x02013;15 kb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and close to the spacing of replication origins on sperm chromatin (1 origin every ~10 kb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. It is notable that the purified ORC, lacking detectable Orc6, can efficiently restore activity to ORC-depleted extracts.</p><p>Recombinant Cdc6 was assayed by titrating into an extract previously immunodepleted with anti-Cdc6 antibodies, an assay specific for Cdc6 or activities co-depleted with it (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3c</xref>). Recombinant Cdc6 restored licensing (50% of the template) at 0.75 ng / ng template DNA. This represents 1 molecule of Cdc6 per ~125 bp DNA, somewhat higher than is available in whole egg extract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. This suggests that, consistent with previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], the recombinant protein is only partially active.</p><p>When purified RLF-B/Cdt1 was titrated into a crude licensing assay, no plateau of activity was reached value, with 20&#x02013;25% of template becoming licensed with ~0.6 pg / ng DNA template, equal to one molecule of RLF-B/Cdt1 per ~35 kb template DNA (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3d</xref>). In a similar assay, recombinant &#x00394;Cdt1 supported licensing (~60% of the template) at ~0.12 ng / ng template DNA (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e</xref>), which represents 1 molecule &#x00394;Cdt1 per ~700 bp template DNA. Like the recombinant Cdc6, recombinant &#x00394;Cdt1 therefore appears to have lower specific activity than the protein purified from whole egg extract.</p><p>Purified Mcm2-7 was produced by mixing equal quantities of the Mcm(3+5) dimer and the Mcm(2+4+6+7) tetramer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. It was assayed by titration into an extract previously immunodepleted with anti-Mcm3 and Mcm7 antibodies, an assay specific for Mcm2-7 or activities co-depleted with them. The activity of purified Mcm2-7 started to plateau at about 1.25 ng / ng template DNA (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>). This corresponds to 1 heterohexamer per ~700 bp template DNA, close to the Mcm2-7 density found on sperm chromatin in whole egg extract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. The difficulty in providing enough Mcm2-7 activity appears largely to be due to having to keep the proteins at high enough concentration (~600 &#x003bc;g / ml in whole egg extract), whilst the specific activity of the purified proteins remains fairly high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p><p>Recombinant geminin was assayed by its ability to inhibit licensing in whole egg extract. Since this appears to be related more to the concentration of RLF-B/Cdt1 in whole extract (~200 pg / &#x003bc;l) rather than the concentration of DNA (data not shown), we have expressed the titration in terms of ng geminin / &#x003bc;l extract. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2g</xref> shows that geminin inhibits origin licensing in whole egg extract at ~1.5 ng / &#x003bc;l, consistent with previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Reconstitution of origin assembly with purified proteins</title><p>We next incubated the purified proteins together with <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei to see if they were sufficient to support efficient origin licensing. Since our major concern here was to reduce the risk of undetected contaminants playing an essential role in the assay, we used all the purified proteins at limiting concentrations as indicated by the arrows in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. Origin licensing was assessed in two different ways. The first was a functional assay, based on the ability of the kinase inhibitor 6-dimethylaminopurine (6-DMAP) to specifically block origin licensing activity as originally defined in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Egg extracts treated with 6-DMAP prior to exit from metaphase ("6-DMAP extracts") fail to degrade geminin, a specific inhibitor of origin licensing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] and so will only replicate chromatin that contains licensed replication origins. Previous work has shown that under the assay conditions used, there is close correlation between the number of licensed origins and the degree of replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Mcm2-7 were first shown to be involved in once-per-cell cycle replication using this type of assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The second assay we used was to detect the quantity of Mcm2-7 loaded onto the sperm chromatin. This binding assay is slightly less satisfactory than the functional assay for two reasons: first, up to 10&#x02013;20 Mcm2-7 heterohexamers can load onto each origin, although only ~2 per origin are required to give maximal replication rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]; second, intermediates in the Mcm2-7 assembly pathway can bind to chromatin, but these intermediates appear to be non-functional and their assembly is independent of other origin proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. We have therefore concentrated most effort on the functional assay.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> shows the results of assays showing that licensed origins can be assembled with good efficiency (corresponding to 18&#x02013;29% of origins) with a combination of purified nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7. When any one of these components was omitted from the reaction, licensing dropped to background levels. Further, functional origin licensing correlated with the assembly of Mcm7 onto the sperm chromatin (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>; see also Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> for Mcm3). The highest activity was obtained with a preparation of RLF-B/Cdt1 taken prior to the final gel filtration step which has very high specific activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). However, both the completely purified RLF-B/Cdt1 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>) and recombinant &#x00394;Cdt1 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4d</xref>) supported efficient origin licensing. Because the efficiency of the reconstitution (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>) was not greatly lower than the activity of the individual proteins put into the reaction (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), we conclude that the licensing of sperm nuclei depends only on the five purified activities and is unlikely to depend on any other contaminating activity.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Reconstitution of licensing using purified proteins. <bold>a, c, d,</bold> Licensing activity of different combinations of purified proteins incubated in the presence of 2.5 mM ATP. DNA synthesis is expressed as % of the DNA template replicated. <bold>b,</bold> Western blot of Mcm7 loaded onto sperm chromatin in whole <italic>Xenopus</italic> extract, the full reconstituted reaction and the reconstituted reaction lacking RLF-B/Cdt1. The reconstituted reactions contained 2.5 mM ATP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Requirements for Cdt1 and geminin association with chromatin. <bold>a, b,</bold><italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei were incubated with the indicated proteins in the presence of 2.5 mM ATP. Chromatin was then isolated and immunoblotted for the presence of bound Orc1, Cdt1 and geminin. The RLF-B/Cdt1 was a slightly more active fraction taken from the geminin bead eluate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Nucleotide requirements of the reconstituted reaction. <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei were incubated with nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1, Mcm2-7 plus or minus geminin in the presence of either ADP, ATP, ATP-&#x003b3;-S at 2.5 mM, or no added nucleotide. <bold>a,</bold> The degree of functional licensing was assessed, expressed as % of the DNA template replicated. <bold>b,</bold> Chromatin was isolated and immunoblotted for the presence of Orc1, Cdt1, Mcm3 and geminin. The Mcm2-7 was a slightly more active fraction taken from the gel filtration step in the purification, and the RLF-B/Cdt1 was from the geminin bead eluate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-6"/></fig><p>Geminin has recently been shown to form a complex with RLF-B/Cdt1 and inhibit its function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows that complete inhibition of licensing in whole extract was achieved with geminin at 1.5 ng / &#x003bc;l. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4d</xref> show that at the same concentration recombinant geminin also inhibited licensing in the reconstituted reaction. This suggests that the inhibition of RLF-B/Cdt1 by geminin is a direct consequence of their interaction and does not require any additional factors.</p></sec><sec><title>Order of assembly</title><p>We next asked whether the binding of Cdt1 and geminin to chromatin was dependent on the other proteins. Although Cdt1 has been shown to bind to chromatin in the absence of Cdc6 in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe,</italic> this has not been shown in metazoans. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref> shows that whilst the binding of Cdt1 to chromatin depended on the presence of ORC, it was not affected by the presence of Cdc6. Unfortunately we could not determine whether the binding of Cdc6 to chromatin was dependent on the presence of RLF-B/Cdt1, because some recombinant Cdc6 bound to decondensed chromatin even in the absence of ORC. This is different to its behaviour in whole extract, where the binding of Cdc6 to chromatin is dependent on ORC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Two possible explanations are that our recombinant Cdc6 preparation may contain denatured or precipitated protein (see above) or that the non-specific binding of Cdc6 to sperm chromatin is normally competed by the binding of other chromatin-associated proteins not present in our reconstitution.</p><p>We have previously shown that when recombinant geminin is added to <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extract, it associates with sperm chromatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref> we have investigated the requirement for this association using purified proteins. Geminin associated only weakly with decondensed chromatin in the presence of ORC. Recruitment of geminin to the chromatin was greatly stimulated by the presence of ORC and RLF-B/Cdt1. The presence of Cdc6 did not affect the quantity of geminin bound to the chromatin. This suggests that the recruitment of geminin to chromatin is mediated by its tight association with RLF-B/Cdt1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], which in turn is independent of Cdc6 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Nucleotide requirements</title><p>We have previously shown that the licensing of <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm chromatin by crude fractions requires ATP, and this ATP requirement cannot be fulfilled by non-hydrolysable nucleotide analogues such as ATP-&#x003b3;-S or AMP-PNP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref> shows a similar requirement for ATP with the reconstituted system. Neither ADP nor ATP-&#x003b3;-S could substitute for ATP. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6b</xref> shows the proteins loaded onto chromatin in reactions containing these different nucleotides. ORC loading was weak in the absence of any nucleotide, but was strongly stimulated by ADP, ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S. In <italic>S. cerevisiae,</italic> ORC binds specifically to origin DNA in the presence of ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], though data about ADP has not been published. Cdt1 binding to chromatin was low in the absence of nucleotide, and was only slightly stimulated by the presence of ADP, despite ORC binding becoming maximal. Further stimulation of Cdt1 binding was seen in the presence of ATP, as origin licensing occurred. However, the highest level of Cdt1 binding was seen in samples containing both ATP and geminin, or in samples containing ATP-&#x003b3;-S, conditions when licensing did not occur (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6b</xref>). This is similar to previous results suggesting that ORC and Cdc6 become destabilised at origins once licensing has occurred [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>In order to investigate the requirement for nucleotides in the binding of Cdc6 to chromatin, we used a crude extract, from which most nucleotides and other small molecules had been removed by gel filtration. Consistent with the results obtained with the purified proteins, gel-filtered extracts only supported efficient origin licensing when supplemented with hydrolysable ATP (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>). High levels of Cdc6 binding to chromatin were seen only in samples containing both ATP and geminin, or in samples containing ATP-&#x003b3;-S (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7b</xref>). Under these conditions no licensing occurred (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>) and high levels of Cdt1 were bound to chromatin (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6b</xref>). The lack of strong Cdc6 binding in the presence of ATP is consistent with our previous results showing that Cdc6 does not bind tightly to chromatin once licensing has occurred ("licensing-dependent origin inactivation") [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Taken together, these results suggest a model where high levels of Cdc6 and Cdt1 bind to chromatin only in the presence of nucleotide triphosphate (ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S), but where the affinity of both proteins is reduced as a consequence of licensing.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Nucleotide requirement for Cdc6 chromatin association in desalted extracts. Sperm nuclei were incubated in desalted whole egg extract plus or minus geminin in the presence of either ADP, ATP, ATP-&#x003b3;-S at 2.5 mM, or no added nucleotide. <bold>a,</bold> The degree of functional licensing was assessed, expressed as % of the DNA template replicated. <bold>b,</bold> Chromatin was isolated and immunoblotted for the presence of Cdc6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>A significant amount of work in both <italic>Xenopus</italic> and yeast has detailed the sequential deposition of ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and finally Mcm2-7 onto replication origins early in the cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. However, the licensing reaction has not before been reconstituted with purified proteins, which is a pre-requisite for a proper biochemical analysis of the reaction. Here we describe the results of a systematic purification of the proteins which have allowed us to license <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei with purified proteins.</p><sec><title>Reconstitution of licensed origins with purified proteins</title><p>We have shown that licensed replication origins can be efficiently assembled on <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei using a combination of nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7. The reconstitution was assessed in two separate ways: first by a functional assay where the initiation of DNA replication is strictly dependent on the presence of licensed replication origins as originally defined in <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>], and secondly by assessing the loading of Mcm3 and Mcm7 onto chromatin. The requirement of all these proteins is consistent with previous work on the assembly of replication origins in a number of eukaryotic organisms. However, it is currently unclear whether this set of proteins (excluding nucleoplasmin) will also generate the pre-RC footprint over replication origins in <italic>S. cerevisiae,</italic> as this may well involve other proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p><p>We provide three lines of evidence strongly suggesting that no other undetected activities contaminating our purified proteins play an essential role in origin licensing. First, during our extensive fractionation of <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and data not shown], we have not detected any unidentified fractions that significantly stimulate origin licensing. Second, the proteins we used have been purified in a number of different ways and contained only a small number of visible contaminating proteins. Third, the efficiency of the reconstituted reaction was high, resulting in ~18&#x02013;28% of potential origins being functionally licensed. In order to minimise the risk of introducing contaminants into the assay, all the individual activities were used at limiting quantities, giving 20&#x02013;80% licensing of template DNA. The efficiency of the reconstituted reaction was therefore not significantly lower than the activities of the individual components, strongly suggesting that no other activities are required. Although it is never possible to prove that purified proteins do not contain functionally important contaminants, we believe that these three independent lines of evidence strongly argue against a requirement for other proteins in the reconstitution.</p><p>The purified ORC we used was devoid of visible Orc6, but despite this, could efficiently support replication licensing in both crude and purified assays. This strongly suggests that Orc6 is not required for origin licensing. It is also noteworthy that no homologue of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Mcm10/Dna43 protein was required for the reconstitution. Mcm10/Dna43 is required for the initiation of DNA replication, in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, and a recent report has shown that when temperature-sensitive mutants of <italic>MCM10/DNA43</italic> are moved to the restrictive temperature in G1, Mcm2 is released from the chromatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Since we find no requirement for Mcm10/Dna43 for Mcm2-7 loading, one possible interpretation of this result is that Mcm10/Dna43 is required for stabilisation, rather than establishment, of Mcm2-7 complexes on chromatin.</p></sec><sec><title>Stages of origin assembly</title><p>The DNA in <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei is held in a tightly condensed state by the sperm basic proteins. Removal of these protamines from the sperm DNA, mediated by nucleoplasmin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], is necessary for ORC to bind to the DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8a,b</xref>). This step is almost certainly unique for sperm nuclei, as most other nuclear templates do not contain abundant protamines. We have shown that the binding of ORC to decondensed sperm chromatin required the presence of nucleotides (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8c</xref>). This requirement could be fulfilled by ATP, ATP-&#x003b3;-S or ADP. In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>Drosophila,</italic> ORC, the specific binding of ORC to origin DNA is dependent on ATP or non-hydrolysable ATP analogues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], though the ability of ADP to substitute for this function has not been described.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Stages in the assembly of licensed replication origins on sperm nuclei. A cartoon of a small segment of <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm DNA is shown following exposure to egg cytoplasm. Nucleotide requirements are shown on the right. <bold>a,</bold> Condensed sperm chromatin, with H2A and H2B replaced by protamines. <bold>b,</bold> Removal of protamines by nucleoplasmin. <bold>c,</bold> Assembly of ORC onto origins, requiring ADP, ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S. <bold>d,</bold> Assembly of Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 onto ORC-containing DNA, requiring ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S. <bold>e,</bold> The loading of Mcm2-7 hetero-hexamers onto chromatin represents origin licensing. 10&#x02013;20 copies of Mcm2-7 can be assembled onto each origin. This step requires hydrolysable ATP. <bold>f,</bold> Once licensing is complete, the affinity of Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 for origins is decreased (licensing-dependent origin inactivation).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-2-15-8"/></fig><p>Once ORC binding has occurred, Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 can be recruited to the DNA (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8d</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. The binding of Cdt1 and Cdc6 to ORC-containing DNA can occur independently of one another [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and this paper]. We show that the recruitment of <italic>Xenopus</italic> Cdc6 to chromatin required ATP or a non-hydrolysable ATP analogue, consistent with results obtained with <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Cdc6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. However, it is currently unclear whether the ATP needs to bind ORC or Cdc6 to promote Cdc6 binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. We also show for the first time that the binding of RLF-B/Cdt1 to chromatin is stimulated by ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S. Quantitation of the purified RLF-B/Cdt1 suggested that one molecule could license ~35 kb DNA, which is expected to contain 3&#x02013;4 origins. One possible explanation for the full activity of sub-stoichiometric amounts of RLF-B/Cdt1 is that it can be rapidly released from replication origins (perhaps coupled to ATP hydrolysis), so that one molecule of RLF-B/Cdt1 can act sequentially at a number of different origins.</p><p>The final step in assembling a licensed origin is the assembly of Mcm2-7 onto chromatin (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8e</xref>). This step requires ATP hydrolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>] and can lead to the binding of 10&#x02013;20 copies of Mcm2-7 to each origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Once Mcm2-7 loading has occurred (which depends on ORC, Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1), their continued binding to DNA does not require the continued presence of ORC or Cdc6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Indeed, the affinity of Cdc6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and RLF-B/Cdt1 (this paper) for chromatin appears to drop once licensing is complete, and maximal levels of these proteins on chromatin are only seen when origin licensing is blocked and in the presence of ATP or ATP-&#x003b3;-S (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8f</xref>). This process, which we have termed "licensing-dependent origin inactivation" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] does not depend on later steps in initiation such as CDK or Cdc7 activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], and seems to occur in the reconstituted reaction.</p></sec><sec><title>Regulation of Origin Licensing</title><p>Origin licensing can be inhibited in at least two ways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]: work in yeast has shown that Cdk activity late in the cell cycle is necessary to prevent the re-licensing (and hence re-firing) of replicated origins, whereas recent work in <italic>Xenopus</italic> has shown that inhibition of RLF-B/Cdt1 by geminin is also a physiologically important mechanism in regulating the replication licensing system during the cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. We show here that geminin can inhibit origin licensing in the fully reconstituted system, suggesting that inhibition by geminin does not require the presence of any other factor. We also show that geminin is also recruited to chromatin in the reconstituted system, and that this is dependent on ORC and RLF-B/Cdt1, but not on Cdc6. The reconstituted reaction should allow us to explore in detail the way that geminin and CDKs regulate the assembly of different origin components during the cell division cycle.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This work shows that origin licensing and Mcm2-7 loading can be reconstituted on <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei with a combination of nucleoplasmin, ORC, Cdc6, RLF-B/Cdt1 and Mcm2-7. The ORC used in the reconstituted reaction apparently lacked the Orc6 subunit, suggesting that it is not required for replication licensing. The reaction required hydrolysable ATP, though ORC loading could be promoted by ADP, and the loading of Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 could be promoted by ATP-&#x003b3;-S. The reconstituted reaction could also be directly inhibited by geminin. The demonstration that the origin licensing and Mcm2-7 loading can be reconstituted with purified proteins now opens the way for a detailed biochemical analysis of this reaction.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Preparation of extracts and DNA templates</title><p>Metaphase-arrested <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts were prepared as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. They were supplemented with 250 &#x003bc;g/ml cycloheximide, 25 mM phosphocreatine, 15 &#x003bc;g/ml creatine phosphokinase, and [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dATP as appropriate, and were then released into interphase with 0.3 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. To make "6-DMAP extract" for licensing assays, extracts were supplemented with 3 mM 6-dimethylaminopurine (6-DMAP) prior to being released into interphase with CaCl<sub>2</sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Immunodepletion of interphase extracts with antibodies against Orc1, Cdc6, Mcm3+7 was performed as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>].</p><p>Desalted interphase extract was prepared as follows: 2 ml pre-swollen Sephadex G-25 (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) was packed into a column and equilibrated in LFB1 (40 mM Hepes KOH pH 8.0, 20 mM K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>/KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> pH 8.0, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EGTA, 2 mM DTT, 10% (w/v) sucrose and 1 &#x003bc;g/ml each of leupeptin, pepstatin and aprotinin) supplemented with 50 mM KCl (i.e. LFB1/50). The column was tested for the separation of bulk protein from [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dATP. 200 &#x003bc;l of metaphase extract supplemented with cycloheximide was released into interphase with CaCl<sub>2</sub> for 15 min at 23&#x000b0;C. Extract was then applied to the Sephadex G-25 column under gravity and 80 &#x003bc;l drip fractions were collected. 5 fractions, from the peak of protein elution were collected, pooled and stored under liquid nitrogen in 20 &#x003bc;l beads until required. The final extract recovered was diluted ~3-fold.</p><p>"Licensing factor extract", which was used as the starting point for all the purifications was prepared as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Briefly, eggs were activated for 5 min by the calcium ionophore A23187, before being spin-crushed in buffer lacking EGTA. Recovered cytoplasm was diluted 1:5 with LFB1/50 and re-centrifuged at 20,000 rpm for 30 min in an SW41 swinging bucket rotor (Beckman). The clarified supernatant was frozen and stored at -80&#x000b0;C until required.</p><p>Demembranated <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei were prepared as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] and frozen in aliquots in liquid nitrogen. Unlicensed "6-DMAP chromatin" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] was assembled by incubating sperm nuclei for 15 min at 23&#x000b0;C in 6-DMAP treated extracts at 30,000 nuclei / &#x003bc;l; extract was then diluted 10-fold in nuclear isolation buffer (NIB: 50 mM KCl, 50 mM Hepes KOH pH 7.6, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM DTT, 0.5 mM spermidine 3HCl, 0.15 mM spermine 4HCl, 1 &#x003bc;g/ml each of leupeptin, pepstatin and aprotinin), and underlayered with 100 &#x003bc;l of the same buffer containing 15% sucrose. The chromatin was pelleted at 6,000 <italic>g</italic> in a swinging bucket rotor at 4&#x000b0;C for 5 min. The diluted extract was then removed and the chromatin pellet was resuspended in NIB and frozen in aliquots in liquid nitrogen.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of proteins</title><p>Nucleoplasmin was purified from "licensing factor extract" by the protocol of Sealy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. RLF-B/Cdt1 was purified as described by Tada et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Because of the very low quantity of RLF-B/Cdt1 produced, protein concentration was roughly estimated using quantitative Western blotting. For some assays (as indicated) the eluate from the geminin affinity column was used instead of the final gel filtration material. Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> &#x00394;Cdt1 was prepared using the bacterial expression construct described by Maiorano et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Inclusion bodies prepared from <italic>E. coli</italic> 4 hr after induction were solubilised in 8 M urea and purified on Nickel NTA agarose (Qiagen) in the presence of 8 M urea. The eluate was dialysed sequentially against THED/400 buffer (20 mM Hepes-KOH pH 8, 20% ethylene glycol, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 0.03% Triton X-100 plus 400 mM KCl) containing urea at 8 M, 4 M, 2 M, 1 M, and finally 0 M. Recombinant <italic>Xenopus</italic> Cdc6 was prepared using the baculovirus expression construct described by Coleman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Cell lysate prepared from infected Sf21 insect cells was purified on Nickel NTA agarose as described for &#x00394;Cdt1, and finally dialysed into 150 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris Cl pH 7.5, 1 mM DTT, 5% glycerol, 0.01% Triton X-100. <italic>Xenopus</italic> Mcm2-7 protein was purified as described by Gillespie and Blow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. MQ1 and MQ3 peaks were mixed in a ratio of 62:38. For some assays (as indicated) the fractions from the gel filtration column were used instead of the MonoQ eluate. Recombinant geminin was prepared in <italic>E. coli</italic> as described by McGarry and Kirschner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p><p><italic>Xenopus</italic> ORC was purified by a modification of the protocol described by Rowles et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. 160 ml of "licensing factor extract" was precipitated with 4.25% polyethylene glycol, resuspended in 50 ml LFB1 plus 150 mM KCl (LFB1/150), and mixed for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C with 12.5 ml phosphocellulose (Whatman P11) equilibrated in LFB1/150. The slurry was poured into a column, washed with LFB1/150 until the UV signal dropped, and activity was eluted by step in LFB1/500. The eluate was then precipitated with 43% (w:v) ammonium sulphate, and the pellet resuspended in 910 &#x003bc;l LFB1/50 plus 2.5 mM Mg-ATP and 0.01% Triton X-100. 4 &#x000d7; 220 &#x003bc;l aliquots were fractionated on a 24 ml Superose 6 gel filtration column (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) run at 0.25 ml / min in LFB1/50 plus 0.01% Triton X-100. 2 &#x000d7; 500 &#x003bc;l fractions from each run containing the UV absorbance peak at ~550 kDa were pooled. The combined gel filtration fractions were applied at 100 &#x003bc;l / min to a 1 ml MonoQ column (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) equilibrated in LFB1/130, and protein eluted in a gradient to LFB1/330 over 20 ml (500 &#x003bc;l fraction size). Fractions containing Orc1 at ~225 mM KCl (confirmed by dot-blotting) were pooled, diluted 1:1 with LFB1 plus 0.01% Triton X-100, and loaded onto a column prepared with 800 &#x003bc;l heparin-agarose FF (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) equilibrated in LFB1/100. The column was developed with a 2.4 ml gradient to LFB1/450 (flow rate 100 &#x003bc;l/min, fraction size 100 &#x003bc;l). Fractions at ~310 mM KCl containing purified ORC (as determined by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie staining) were pooled and diluted 1:3 in LFB1/10 (4.23 ng ORC / &#x003bc;l).</p></sec><sec><title>Assays for individual activities</title><p>The assays for ORC, Cdc6 and Mcm2-7 activity were performed by incubating 2.5 &#x003bc;l test samples (purified protein diluted in 20 mM Hepes KOH pH 8.0, 10 mM KCl, 2 mM DTT, 10% (w:v) sucrose and 1 &#x003bc;g/ml each of leupeptin, pepstatin and aprotinin) with 2.5 &#x003bc;l egg extract depleted of ORC, Cdc6 or Mcm2-7 and 0.5 &#x003bc;l <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei (70 ng DNA / &#x003bc;l) for 30 min; the reaction was then added to 12.5 &#x003bc;l 6-DMAP-treated extract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] supplemented with [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dATP, and the incubation continued for a further 90 min. Total DNA synthesis was determined by TCA precipitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. The assay for nucleoplasmin activity was performed exactly as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. In brief, 0.3 &#x003bc;l <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei (70 ng DNA / &#x003bc;l) plus 1 &#x003bc;l of a crude fraction containing ORC, Cdc6 and RLF-B/Cdt1 (1.5&#x000d7; BPAS diluted in LFB1/50 + 5 mM Mg-ATP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] plus 1 &#x003bc;l of a crude fraction containing Mcm2-7 (SP Sepharose eluate) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and 1 &#x003bc;l purified nucleoplasmin were incubated for 30 min; the reaction was then added to 6 &#x003bc;l 6-DMAP-treated extract and processed as above. The assay for RLF-B activity was performed by incubating 3 &#x003bc;l test samples (purified RLF-B diluted in TAB/I 00 buffer) (TAB/100: 2.5 mM Mg-ATP, 4 mg / ml bovine serum albumin, 0.02% Triton-X 100 plus 100 mM KCl) with 2 &#x003bc;l crude Mcm2-7 (Q Sepharose eluate) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and 0.5 &#x003bc;l "6-DMAP chromatin" (50 ng DNA / &#x003bc;l) for 30 min; the reaction was then added to 6-DMAP-treated extract and processed as above.</p></sec><sec><title>Reconstitution</title><p>The reconstituted reaction consisted of 0.4 &#x003bc;l purified nucleoplasmin (340 ng / &#x003bc;l), 0.9 &#x003bc;l purified ORC (4.2 ng / &#x003bc;l), 0.7 &#x003bc;l purified Cdc6 (50 ng / &#x003bc;l), 2 &#x003bc;l Mcm2-7 (17 ng / &#x003bc;l), and 1 &#x003bc;l of either purified RLF-B/Cdt1 or &#x00394;Cdt1 (8.7 ng / &#x003bc;l) and 0.5 &#x003bc;l demembranated <italic>Xenopus</italic> sperm nuclei (70 ng DNA / &#x003bc;l). ATP, ATP-&#x003b3;-S and ADP were added to a final concentration of 2.5 mM as required. Some reactions were supplemented with 0.5 &#x003bc;l geminin (15 ng / &#x003bc;l). When individual components were removed, the volume was made up with the appropriate buffer for each protein. Reactions were performed for 30 min at 23&#x000b0;C. For assessment of functional licensing, the reactions were added to 12.5 &#x003bc;l 6-DMAP-treated extract supplemented with [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]dATP, and the incubation continued for a further 90 min. Total DNA synthesis [dependent on the degree of licensing that had occurred, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]] was determined by TCA precipitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>].</p><p>For chromatin blotting experiments, the reconstitution reactions were scaled up 10&#x000d7; to 50 &#x003bc;l. After the 30 min licensing incubation, each reaction was diluted in 400 &#x003bc;l NIB supplemented with 0.1% Triton X-100, and underlayered with 120 &#x003bc;l of the same buffer containing 10% sucrose. The chromatin was pelleted at 2,500 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min in a swinging bucket rotor at 4&#x000b0;C (Megafuge; Heraeus). The diluted extract was removed and the chromatin pellet was resuspended in 6&#x000d7; SDS-PAGE loading buffer. The samples were run on 4-12% Bis-Tris gradient gels (Novex / Invitrogen). The portion of the gel below the 25 kDa marker was cut off and stained with Coomassie to check the level of histones H3 and H4 as a control for chromatin recovery; the remainder of the gel was analysed by immunoblotting.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank: Douglas Lamont and Nick Morrice for MALDI-TOF analysis; Tatsuya Hirano for XKlp1 antibody; Shusuke Tada for RLF-B/Cdt1 fractions; Alan J. Score for recombinant XCdc6; and Ben Hodgson, Anne Donaldson, Tom Owen-Hughes, Pedro Jares and Anna Woodward for helpful comments. This work was funded by the Cancer Research Campaign [CRC] (grant SP2385/0101). PJG was supported by a studentship from the Department of Biochemistry, University of Dundee.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JFX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Building the perfect switch.</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R367</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11369250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00196-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tye</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initiating DNA synthesis: from recruiting to activating the MCM complex.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2001</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>1447</fpage><lpage>1454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282021</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of chromosomal DNA replication in the early Xenopus embryo.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3293</fpage><lpage>3297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.13.3293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for the nuclear envelope in controlling DNA replication within the cell cycle.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3357511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/332546a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>JPJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahbubani</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification of an Mcm-containing complex as a component of the DNA replication licensing system.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>375</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7760937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/375418a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the yeast MCM3-related protein as a component of Xenopus DNA Replication Licensing Factor.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7758114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90081-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Licensing of DNA replication by a multi-protein complex of MCM/P1 proteins in Xenopus eggs.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3320</fpage><lpage>3331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9214647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/16.11.3320</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Th&#x000f6;mmes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RLF-M component of the replication licensing system forms complexes containing all six MCM/P1 polypeptides.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3312</fpage><lpage>3319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9214646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/16.11.3312</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two steps in the assembly of complexes at yeast replication origins in vivo.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8044842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90299-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Components and dynamics of DNA replication complexes in S-cerevisiae: Redistribution of MCM proteins and Cdc45p during S phase.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9335335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)80009-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labib</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tercero</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JFX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uninterrupted MCM2-7 function required for DNA replication fork progression.</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10834843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.288.5471.1643</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication licensing &#x02013; defining the proliferative state?</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Piatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Santocanale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasmyth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An essential role for the Cdc6 protein in forming the pre-replicative complexes of budding yeast.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8538771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/379180a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Xenopus Cdc6 protein is essential for the initiation of a single round of DNA replication in cell-free extracts.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8858148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81322-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Evan</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between the origin recognition complex and the replication licensing system in Xenopus.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81346-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>JPJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahbubani</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RLF-B component of the replication licensing system is distinct from Cdc6 and functions after Cdc6 binds to chromatin.</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10074431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(99)80092-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishitani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lygerou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Cdt1 protein is required to license DNA for replication in fission yeast.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35007110</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiorano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mechali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>XCDT1 is required for the assembly of pre-replicative complexes in Xenopus laevis.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35007104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiorano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;chali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repression of origin assembly in metaphase depends on inhibition of RLF-B/Cdt1 by geminin.</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35055000</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drury</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cdc6p-dependent loading of Mcm proteins onto pre-replicative chromatin in budding yeast.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>5611</fpage><lpage>5616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.11.5611</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Newport</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a preinitiation step in DNA replication that is independent of origin recognition complex and cdc6, but dependent on cdk2.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.140.2.271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in association of the Xenopus origin recognition complex with chromatin on licensing of replication origins.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10341218</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wohlschlegel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cvetic</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of eukaryotic replication by geminin binding to Cdt1.</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>2309</fpage><lpage>2312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.290.5500.2309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleoplasmin-mediated chromatin remodelling is required for Xenopus sperm nuclei to become licensed for DNA replication.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10606645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.2.472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leno</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sperm decondensation in Xenopus egg cytoplasm is mediated by nucleoplasmin.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2032284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90089-H</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leno</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleoplasmin remodels sperm chromatin in Xenopus egg extracts.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1591776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90288-N</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prokhorova</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequential MCM/P1 subcomplex assembly is required to form a heterohexamer with replication licensing activity.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>2491</fpage><lpage>2498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.4.2491</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sealy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalkley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Xenopus nucleoplasmin: egg vs. oocyte.</article-title><source>Biochem</source><year>1986</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3064</fpage><lpage>3072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3521726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00358a049</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laskey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleosomes are assembled by an acidic protein which binds histones and transfers them to DNA.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1978</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">692721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role for a Xenopus Orc2-related protein in controlling DNA replication.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/379357a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel 81-kDa component of the Xenopus origin recognition complex.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>24891</fpage><lpage>24897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.38.24891</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou-Yang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Canas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Orc4p and Orc5p subunits of the Xenopus and human origin recognition complex are related to Orc1p and Cdc6p.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>32421</fpage><lpage>32429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9829972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.49.32421</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vashee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pamela Simancek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Challberg</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of the Human Origin Recognition Complex.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>26666</fpage><lpage>26673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M102493200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Architecture of the yeast origin recognition complex bound to origins of DNA replication.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>7159</fpage><lpage>7168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9372948</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walczak</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>XKCM1: A Xenopus kinesin-related protein that regulates microtubule dynamics during mitotic spindle assembly.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8548824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80991-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Raats</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heasman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsenti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Xklp1, a chromosomal Xenopus kinesin-like protein essential for spindle organization and chromosome positioning.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7720067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90376-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGarry</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geminin, an inhibitor of DNA replication, is degraded during mitosis.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9635433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81209-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication origins in Xenopus egg extract are 5&#x02013;15 kb apart and are activated in clusters that fire at different times.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11149917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.152.1.15</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahbubani</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000f6;mmes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell cycle regulation of the replication licensing system: involvement of a Cdk-dependent inhibitor.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9008708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.136.1.125</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preventing re-replication of DNA in a single cell cycle: evidence for a replication licensing factor.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8354699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.122.5.993</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of initiation of DNA replication before and after nuclear formation in Xenopus egg cell free extracts.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>1321</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.123.6.1321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastians</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Topper</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorbsky</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruderman</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell cycle-regulated proteolysis of mitotic target proteins.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3927</fpage><lpage>3941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10564281</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATP-dependent recognition of eukaryotic origins of DNA replication by a multiprotein complex.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1579162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/357128a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinate binding of ATP and origin DNA regulates the ATPase activity of the origin recognition complex.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9038340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81889-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Xenopus Cdc7 function is dependent on licensing but not on XORC, XCdc6, or CDK activity and is required for XCdc45 loading.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1528</fpage><lpage>1540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10859170</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasmyth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loading of an Mcm protein onto DNA replication origins is regulated by Cdc6p and CDKs.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80526-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JFX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide-dependent prereplicative complex assembly by Cdc6p, a homolog of eukaryotic and prokaryotic clamp-loaders.</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(00)80110-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinreich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Cdc6p nucleotide-binding motif is required for loading Mcm proteins onto chromatin.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9892652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.2.441</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kearsey</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Labib</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin binding of the fission yeast replication factor mcm4 occurs during anaphase and requires ORC and cdc18.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/19.7.1681</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Homesley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tye</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mcm10 and the MCM2-7 complex interact to initiate DNA synthesis and to release replication factors from origins.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10783164</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr-Weaver</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drosophila ORC specifically binds to ACE3, an origin of DNA replication control element.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2639</fpage><lpage>2649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.13.20.2639</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cdc6p modulates the structure and DNA binding activity of the origin recognition complex in vitro.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1631</fpage><lpage>1641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887157</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Diffley</surname><given-names>JFX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stepwise assembly of initiation proteins at budding yeast replication origins in vitro.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>14115</fpage><lpage>14120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.26.14115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Musahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohring</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Knippers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of human nuclear proteins P1Mcm3 and P1Cdc46.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>1995</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7705359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tye</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical interactions among Mcm proteins and effects of Mcm dosage on DNA replication in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>5081</fpage><lpage>5090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Th&#x000f6;mmes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahbubani</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the Xenopus replication licensing system.</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1997</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9251047</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


