<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Biochem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Biochemistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2091</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3060121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2091-12-12</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21375735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2091-12-12</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Peroxisomal Targeting Signal 1 in sterol carrier protein 2 is autonomous and essential for receptor recognition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Chris P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>c.williams@embl-hamburg.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Schueller</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>nicholton@googlemail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Colin A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>cthompson@ichr.uwa.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>Marlene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>m.vandenberg@amc.uva.nl</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Van Haren</surname><given-names>Simon D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>simonvharen@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>Ralf</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>ralf.erdmann@rub.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>Charles S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>charles.bond@uwa.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>Ben</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>b.distel@amc.uva.nl</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><name><surname>Schliebs</surname><given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>wolfgang.schliebs@ruhr-uni-bochum.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10"><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>wilmanns@embl-hamburg.de</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A11"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>Will A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>will.stanley@uwa.edu.au</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>EMBL-Hamburg, c/o DESY, Notkestra&#x003b2;e 85, 22603 Hamburg, Germany</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Medical Biochemistry, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, Meibergdreef 15, 1105 AZ Amsterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Phylogica, 100 Roberts Road, Subiaco, 6008 WA, Australia</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Systems Biochemistry, Institute for Physiological Chemistry, Faculty of Medicine, Ruhr University of Bochum, 44780 Bochum, Germany</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>School of Biomedical, Biomolecular and Chemical Sciences, MCS Building (M310), University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, 6009 WA, Australia</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>ARC CoE in Plant Energy Biology, MCS Building (M316), University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, 6009 WA, Australia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2011 Williams et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Williams et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2091/12/12"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The majority of peroxisomal matrix proteins destined for translocation into the peroxisomal lumen are recognised <italic>via </italic>a C-terminal Peroxisomal Target Signal type 1 by the cycling receptor Pex5p. The only structure to date of Pex5p in complex with a cargo protein is that of the C-terminal cargo-binding domain of the receptor with sterol carrier protein 2, a small, model peroxisomal protein. In this study, we have tested the contribution of a second, ancillary receptor-cargo binding site, which was found in addition to the characterised Peroxisomal Target Signal type 1.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>To investigate the function of this secondary interface we have mutated two key residues from the ancillary binding site and analyzed the level of binding first by a yeast-two-hybrid assay, followed by quantitative measurement of the binding affinity and kinetics of purified protein components and finally, by <italic>in vivo </italic>measurements, to determine translocation capability. While a moderate but significant reduction of the interaction was found in binding assays, we were not able to measure any significant defects <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our data therefore suggest that at least in the case of sterol carrier protein 2 the contribution of the second binding site is not essential for peroxisomal import. At this stage, however, we cannot rule out that other cargo proteins may require this ancillary binding site.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Pex5p, the major import receptor for peroxisomal matrix proteins, is known to carry folded proteins across the peroxisomal membrane by a signal assembled shuttling mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It has been found to recognise the type 1 Peroxisomal Targeting Signal (PTS1) - a C-terminal tripeptide of consensus sequence -[S/A/C]-[K/H/R]-[L/M]-CO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>, carried by some 40 human proteins destined for the peroxisomal lumen. The PTS1 sequence binds to Pex5p in an extended conformation, which is accommodated in a deep cavity in the tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) domain of Pex5p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). An additional interface, remote from the PTS1 binding site, of about 500 &#x000c5;<sup>2 </sup>has been found to form between Pex5p and the model cargo protein sterol carrier protein 2 (SCP2), as demonstrated by the crystal structure and solution studies of SCP2 in complex with the C-terminal region of Pex5p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In the following we will refer to the interface as "ancillary" or "secondary". This interface utilises the first and fourth &#x003b1;-helices of SCP2 and helices 15 and 16 from the Pex5p C-terminal helical bundle (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) and its formation confers an increased binding affinity of around 6-fold when compared to a minimal PTS1 hexapeptide (PGNAKL-CO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>), derived from the C-terminus of SCP2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Taken together, these observations may imply the presence of an additional receptor recognition element in SCP2, supplemental to the PTS1.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Structural features of the Pex5p-SCP2 ancillary interface</bold>. <bold>(A) </bold>Cartoon of the X-ray crystal structure of Pex5p(C) in complex with mSCP2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Pex5p(C) is shown in green and mSCP2 in blue. A partial surface representation for mSCP2 is shown, denoting the residues of mSCP2 that approach Pex5p(C) to &#x0003c; 4 &#x000c5; - that is, the extended C-terminal PTS1 buried within Pex5p(C) and the ancillary helix-helix interface. The ancillary interface is highlighted - residues contributed by mSCP2 are coloured in burgundy and those contributed by Pex5p(C) in yellow. <bold>(B) </bold>Amino acid sequence alignment of the C-terminal 3-helix segment of Pex5p, using the standard letter code. The following colour scheme is used: CFILMPVWY (green), HNQST (magenta), DE (red), KR (blue) and AG (yellow). The alignment was generated with CLUSTAL-W [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and manually adjusted, the figure generated in ALINE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Positions of &#x003b1;-helices 15, 16 and 17 (from the human Pex5p(C)/mSCP2 crystal structure, PDB accession <ext-link ext-link-type="pdb" xlink:href="2C0L">2C0L</ext-link>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]) as defined by DSSP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] are indicated at the top of the figure. Residues marked with an arrowhead (black triangle) were mutated in this study. Species identifiers: <italic>Tb, Trypanosoma brucei; Yl, Yarrowia lipolytica; At, Arabidopsis thaliana; Cl, Citrullus lanatus; Nt, Nicotiana tabacum; Br, Brachydanio rerio; Cg, Cricetulus griseus; Cp, Cavia porcellus; Hs, Homo sapiens; Mm, Mus musculus; Ce, Caenorhabditis elegans; Dm, Drosophila melanogaster; Pc, Penicillium crysogenum; Hp, Hansenula polymorpha; Pp, Pichia pastoris; Ld, Leishmania donovani; Nc, Neurospora crassa; Rn, Rattus novegicus; Sc, Saccharomyces cerevisiae; Sp, Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>. The human Pex5p sequence is indicated with an asterisk (black star). In mammalian sequences, (L) and (S) denote whether the numbering used refers to the long or short forms of Pex5p. <bold>(C) </bold>Stereo view focusing on the ancillary interface between Pex5p(C) and mSCP2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The protein colour scheme is as in <bold>(A)</bold>. Sidechains are shown for residues at the interface. See text for details. <bold>(D) </bold>View showing the different arrangement of key Pex5p residues at the ancillary interface in the presence (green) and absence (red) of mSCP2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. See text for details. Crystal structure figures were prepared in PyMOL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-12-12-1"/></fig><p>Inspection of the secondary interface of the Pex5p(C)-SCP2 complex structure reveals several intermolecular hydrogen bonds (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>), in particular: the carboxylate group of Glu35 from SCP2 interacts with the side chains of two Pex5p residues, Arg608 and Tyr620; Lys38 from SCP2 forms a salt bridge with Asp624 from Pex5p; finally, Lys28 from SCP2 interacts with the main chain carbonyl group of Gly615 from Pex5p(C). Comparison with the Pex5p(C) apo-structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] reveals that in the absence of SCP2, two residues from this interface, Arg608 and Asp624, re-orient their sidechains to form an intramolecular salt bridge, inducing a re-orientation of the sidechain of Tyr620 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). An alignment of a set of Pex5p sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) indicates that while Tyr620 and Asp624 are only partly conserved, a basic residue at the position equivalent to Arg608 in human Pex5p is invariant.</p><p>In this study, we have made point mutations of two key residues of the ancillary SCP2 binding interface in Pex5p, Arg608 and Asp624, to tryptophans to assess the relative importance of the additional interface in the recognition of SCP2 by Pex5p. To dissect the contributions of the PTS1 and these additional interactions, we also used a version of SCP2 lacking the C-terminal PTS1, for comparison. By four different approaches we demonstrate that while receptor-cargo binding and SCP2 transfer into the peroxisome are absolutely dependent on the presence of the PTS1, the ancillary interface is found to be dispensable - mutations effecting binding do not inhibit peroxisomal import <italic>in vivo</italic>. These results indicate that the ancillary interface is unlikely to play an important role in the import of the PTS1 protein SCP2.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Yeast two-hybrid analysis of human Pex5p interactions with SCP2</title><p>First, we created mutant versions of the cargo-binding domain of Pex5p (Pex5p(C), consisting of residues 315-639) and tested their capacity to interact with different versions of SCP2 in the yeast two-hybrid system (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). As a control, we showed that the presence of the PTS1 of SCP2 is a pre-requisite for binding to Pex5p(C), as no interaction could be detected in its absence, thus confirming previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The introduction of the mutation R608W into Pex5p(C) did result in a three-fold reduction of the interaction with both pre- and mSCP2. In contrast, the Pex5p(C) D624W mutation showed little affect, either leading to a slight decrease (mSCP2) or increase (preSCP2) of the interaction. To confirm that the observed decrease with the Pex5p(C) R608W construct was not due to problems with expression or stability of the protein, we performed Western blotting analysis with Pex5p antibodies on yeast lysates from cells expressing the different Pex5p(C) variants. We could see that all Pex5p constructs were expressed at similar levels (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Summary of yeast two-hybrid data</bold>. Two-hybrid interactions of wild-type (WT) and mutant (R608W and D624W) forms of Pex5p(C) with SCP2. Activity of the reported gene &#x003b2;-galactosidase (as defined by absorbance at 420 nm per mg of protein per min) was used to determine the strength of interaction. Values correspond to the mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-12-12-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Western blot showing Pex5p wild-type and mutant expression levels</bold>. <italic>Upper panel </italic>- Expression levels of wild-type (WT) and mutant (R608W and D624W) forms of Pex5p in yeast cells used for two-hybrid analysis. The Gal4AD-Pex5p(C) fusions are indicated with a solid arrow. The open arrow indicates a breakdown product of the fusions and the asterisk indicates a background band recognised by the Pex5p antibody. <italic>Lower panel </italic>- Loading control, showing the same samples above probed with the anti-hexokinase antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-12-12-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>In vitro Pex5p-SCP2 binding</title><p>We tested the capacity of these mutants to bind mSCP2 <italic>in vitro </italic>using isothermal titration microcalorimetry (ITC) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). We observed that the Pex5p(C) R608W mutation resulted in a two fold reduction in SCP2 binding, in agreement with our yeast-two-hybrid data. In addition, we found the binding stoichiometry reduced to 0.61, indicating that only about two-thirds of the receptor was competent for SCP2 cargo binding, compared to a value approaching one for wild-type. The binding stoichiometry was further lowered to 0.41 when using the second Pex5p(C) mutant, D624W, coupled with an apparent tighter binding when compared to wild-type Pex5p(C). Additionally, we measured the binding affinity of the Pex5p(C) mutants against a peptide derived from the C-terminus of SCP2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, PGNAKL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]), a binding event that is independent of the ancillary interface. The Pex5p(C) R608W mutant bound to the peptide with a similar affinity as the wild-type protein. Furthermore, the binding stoichiometry of this mutant was closer to that of wild-type Pex5p(C), suggesting that the R608W mutant is impaired in binding when utilising the secondary interface but not when using the PTS1 binding site alone.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of ITC data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><bold>Pex5p(C)</bold>:</th><th align="center">Ligand</th><th align="center">n</th><th align="center">&#x00394;H<break/>(kJ/mol)</th><th align="center">T&#x00394;S<break/>(kJ/mol)</th><th align="center">&#x00394;G<break/>(kJ/mol)</th><th align="center">K<sub>d </sub><break/>(nM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Wild-type (5) <sup>a</sup></bold></td><td align="center">mSCP2</td><td align="center">0.93 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="center">-43.4</td><td align="center">-1.8</td><td align="center">-42.3</td><td align="center">95 &#x000b1; 21</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>R608W (4)</bold></td><td align="center">mSCP2</td><td align="center">0.61 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="center">-71.7</td><td align="center">-31.8</td><td align="center">-39.9</td><td align="center">179 &#x000b1; 19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>D624W (4)</bold></td><td align="center">mSCP2</td><td align="center">0.41 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="center">-55.6</td><td align="center">-12.2</td><td align="center">-43.4</td><td align="center">45 &#x000b1; 8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Wild-type (2)</bold></td><td align="center">PGNAKL</td><td align="center">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="center">-42.5</td><td align="center">-5.6</td><td align="center">-36.9</td><td align="center">547 &#x000b1; 6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>R608W (2)</bold></td><td align="center">PGNAKL</td><td align="center">0.81 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="center">-51.6</td><td align="center">-15.1</td><td align="center">-36.5</td><td align="center">635 &#x000b1; 25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>D624W (2)</bold></td><td align="center">PGNAKL</td><td align="center">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="center">-54.7</td><td align="center">-18.6</td><td align="center">-36.1</td><td align="center">763 &#x000b1; 0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><bold>a </bold></sup>Numbers in brackets indicate the number of measurements.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To determine whether structural alterations induced by the mutations were the cause of the observed binding defects, we subjected the mutants to circular dichroism spectropolarimetry (CD) and static light scattering (SLS) analysis. While both mutants showed similar properties when tested with SLS (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) (i.e. they are found to be monomeric and similarly mondispersed), a difference could be seen with the D624W mutant using CD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Wild-type Pex5p(C) is estimated to have 60.3 &#x000b1; 2.1% &#x003b1;-helical content and R608W 57.0 &#x000b1; 1.0%, in good agreement with the 60.2 - 64.4% of residues in &#x003b1;-helices (as a proportion the 329 residue fragment consistently used in crystallisation experiments) found within the various chains of apo-human Pex5p(C) in PDB entries <ext-link ext-link-type="pdb" xlink:href="2C0M">2C0M</ext-link>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] and <ext-link ext-link-type="pdb" xlink:href="2J9Q">2J9Q</ext-link>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. However, D624W carries only 48.7 &#x000b1; 1.5% &#x003b1;-helix (with a concomitant increase in irregular structure), suggesting that the D624W mutation may alter the folding properties of Pex5p(C). These data show that a specific cargo recognition defect can be seen with the Pex5p R608W mutant when binding full-length SCP2 and that structural impairment was not the cause of this binding defect.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of static light scattering data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th align="center">Pex5p(C) WT</th><th align="center">Pex5p(C) R608W</th><th align="center">Pex5p(C) D624W</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Molecular weight (Mw)</bold></td><td align="center">32.2<sup>a </sup>(&#x000b1; 8%)</td><td align="center">35.6 (&#x000b1; 25%)</td><td align="center">30.3 (&#x000b1; 18%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Number weighted mean (Mn)</bold></td><td align="center">31.0 (&#x000b1; 8%)</td><td align="center">34.4 (&#x000b1; 20%)</td><td align="center">29.9 (&#x000b1; 16%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Polydispersity (Mw/Mn)</bold></td><td align="center">1.0 (&#x000b1; 11%)</td><td align="center">1.0 (&#x000b1; 32%)</td><td align="center">1.0 (&#x000b1; 25%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Theoretical Mw</bold></td><td align="center">35.2</td><td align="center">35.2</td><td align="center">35.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Values are expressed in kDa</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Circular dichroism analysis of wild-type and mutant Pex5p(C)</bold>. CD spectra of wild-type and the mutant (R608W and D624W) forms of Pex5p(C). While wild-type and R608W show very similar secondary structure content, D624W does not. See text for details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-12-12-4"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of secondary structure estimations from CD spectropolarimetry</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Pex5p(C) sample</th><th align="center">% &#x003b1;-helix <sup>a</sup></th><th align="center">% &#x003b2;-strand</th><th align="center">% other</th><th align="center">NRMSD <sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Wild-type</bold></td><td align="center">60.3 &#x000b1; 1.5 <sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">7.0 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">32.6 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="center">0.012 &#x000b1; 0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>R608W</bold></td><td align="center">57.0 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">9.0 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">34.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="center">0.011 &#x000b1; 0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>D624W</bold></td><td align="center">48.7 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td align="center">9.0 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">42.3 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="center">0.017 &#x000b1; 0.002</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Secondary structure estimates derived from DICHROWEB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] (see Methods)</p><p><sup>b</sup>Mean and standard deviation over three measurements are given</p><p><sup>c</sup>Normalised root mean square deviation calculated in DICHROWEB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To further clarify the impaired binding between Pex5p(C) mutants and SCP2, we examined the interaction kinetics using the Octet RED96 assay system (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Once again, in the absence of the PTS1, no binding could be measured - regardless of whether the presequence in SCP2 or mutations in Pex5p(C) were present. We detected that relative to wild-type Pex5p(C), each mutant displayed a 2.0 - 3.5 fold decreases in association rates (k<sub>on</sub>). Most strongly impaired in k<sub>on </sub>(a 3.5 fold decrease) was the infantile Refsum disease mutant Pex5p(C)S600W [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], a mutation in the 7C-loop (and therefore distant from the ancillary interface) we have previously found not to bind to mSCP2 in ITC experiments and to impair import of SCP2 and catalase <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In contrast, all mutants displayed very similar dissociation rates (k<sub>off</sub>) to wild-type Pex5p(C), with the exception of D624W, which had a 2.7 fold more rapid k<sub>off </sub>from mSCP2 compared to wild-type. Thus, in line with our previous data, the ancillary interface residues Arg608 and Asp624 do have roles in receptor recognition and binding but at least in the case of Arg608, play a lesser role in the overall stability of the Pex5p(C)/SCP2 complex. The impaired k<sub>on </sub>and k<sub>off </sub>demonstrated for D624W presumably result from the structural deviation shown above.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Summary of binding kinetics measured using Octet RED96</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Immobilised<break/>biotinylated Pex5p(C)</th><th align="left">Ligand</th><th align="right">Association rate, k<sub>on </sub><break/>(1/Ms)</th><th align="right">Dissociation rate, k<sub>off </sub><break/>(1/s)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Wild-type</bold></td><td align="left">mSCP2</td><td align="right">2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>(&#x000b1; 2.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="right">5.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 2.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Wild-type</bold></td><td align="left">preSCP2</td><td align="right">3.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>(&#x000b1; 2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="right">7.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>S600W</bold></td><td align="left">mSCP2</td><td align="right">6.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3 </sup>(&#x000b1; 3.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup>)</td><td align="right">6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>S600W</bold></td><td align="left">preSCP2</td><td align="right">7.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3 </sup>(&#x000b1; 4.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup>)</td><td align="right">5.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>R608W</bold></td><td align="left">mSCP2</td><td align="right">7.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3 </sup>(&#x000b1; 4.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup>)</td><td align="right">7.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>R608W</bold></td><td align="left">preSCP2</td><td align="right">9.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3 </sup>(&#x000b1; 6.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup>)</td><td align="right">5.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>D624W</bold></td><td align="left">mSCP2</td><td align="right">1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>(&#x000b1; 8.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup>)</td><td align="right">1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-4 </sup>(&#x000b1; 2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>D624W</bold></td><td align="left">preSCP2</td><td align="right">1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>(&#x000b1; 1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="right">8.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>(&#x000b1; 2.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6</sup>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Peroxisomal import of SCP2 in fibroblast complementation assays</title><p>We have complemented Pex5p impaired fibroblast cultures from Zellweger syndrome patient PBD005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] with the long isoform of human Pex5p (Pex5p(L)) and Pex5p(L) mutated at residues Arg608 and Asp624. 12, 24 and 48 hours after transfection, the ability of these complemented cells to import the reporter molecule GFP-mSCP2 into peroxisomes was assayed by immunofluorescence microscopy (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). We also determined the localisation of Pex5p(L) using immunofluorescence. The cytosolic distribution of Pex5p(L) was not altered by the mutations and all ancillary interface mutants gave rise to a similar punctuate pattern for GFP-mSCP2, characteristic of peroxisomal localisation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Even when the transfected cells were incubated at 40&#x000b0;C instead of 37&#x000b0;C (to challenge the cells with a stress condition) the Pex5p mutants retained their ability to import GFP-SCP2 into peroxisomes (data not shown). In contrast, both negative controls, using Pex5p(L) S600W and wild-type Pex5p(L) with GFP-mSCP2&#x00394;AKL, showed diffuse GFP fluorescence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>), indicating that in each case GFP-SCP2 is retained in the cytosol. Thus, despite the moderate impairment of <italic>in vitro </italic>binding caused by mutation at the ancillary interface, the same mutations do not impair Pex5p(L) mediated peroxisomal import, at least of SCP2 as an import substrate - although subtle alterations in import kinetics cannot entirely be excluded by our localisation assay. However, the presence of the PTS1 and retention of the capacity of Pex5p(L) to act as a PTS1 binding receptor are essential.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold><italic>In vivo </italic>localisation assays</bold>. Subcellular localisation of peroxisomal marker enzymes demonstrate that mutations within the ancillary SCP2 binding site of Pex5p do not impair peroxisomal import. Pex5p-deficient fibroblast cells were co-transfected with a plasmid expressing GFP-SCP2 either with (A) or without its PTS1 sequence (B) and plasmids expressing wild-type (WT) or mutant forms of Pex5p, carrying the point mutations R608W, D624W or S600W. Forty eight hours after transfection GFP-SCP2 was visualised by direct fluorescence (green colour), while Pex5p (A) and Pex14p (B) were detected by immunofluorescence microscopy. Scale bars (in bottom right micrographs) indicate 10 &#x003bc;M.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-12-12-5"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our data confirm previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] that the PTS1 of SCP2 is essential for the interaction with the PTS1 receptor Pex5p and for its Pex5p-mediated targeting to the peroxisomal matrix and we additionally characterise the role of the secondary binding site in cargo binding. While mutation of Arg608 in Pex5p(C) impairs the binding affinity, stoichiometry (from two hybrid and ITC experiments) and association rate (from Octet RED96 experiments) with SCP2, its' introduction <italic>in vivo </italic>does not impair the capacity of Pex5p(L) to import SCP2 into peroxisomes, suggesting that the ancillary interface, formed between SCP2 and Pex5p plays only a limited role in the import of SCP2.</p><p>The R608W and D624W mutations in Pex5p(C), while not causing an obvious phenotype <italic>in vivo</italic>, do cause some interesting and unexpected behaviour <italic>in vitro</italic>. Firstly, the apparent increase in binding affinity caused by the D624W mutation, an effect that seems to contradict the reduction observed with the R608W mutant. Our CD data indicate that the D624W mutant has altered folding properties, in relation to the wild type and R608W mutant, which may affect the binding to SCP2 in an unexpected way. A reduction in binding affinity can readily be justified, in terms of a loss of contact sites in Pex5p(C). However, the reductions in binding stoichiometries of the mutants are less easily explained. We cannot absolutely rule out the possibility that the Pex5p mutants are able to oligomerise, resulting in a change in the stoichiometry of the interaction. However, our SLS data indicate that both mutants, like the wild type protein, are monomeric in solution, which makes this explanation unlikely. From the Octet RED96 experiments, we see that both mutants exhibit a slower association rate. This, together with the faster dissociation rate observed with the D624W mutant, combined with apparent changes in its' folding properties, could contribute to differences in the stoichiometries.</p><p>We are then left with the question as to what the possible function(s) of the secondary interface in PTS1 protein import may be. The capacity for Pex5p to import folded proteins is well known and is likely to represent an essential part of its task since to date no chaperones have been identified within the peroxisomal matrix that could aid in the folding of imported substrates. Therefore, two possible roles for the ancillary interface could be envisaged; increasing the overall stability of the receptor-cargo complex by providing extra contact sites between Pex5p and the PTS1 protein and/or a "quality control" step, allowing Pex5p to check PTS1 proteins for correct folding before importing them into the matrix, since the region in SCP2 recognised by the ancillary interface, unlike the PTS1, is fully folded. However, it may be expected that impairment of either process would result in an inhibition of the import process, which is not the case in our hands. Our data do not rule out the possibility that Pex5p uses this secondary interface with other cargo proteins and indeed, the apparent conservation of the Arg608 residue suggests a potential role in the function of Pex5p. In addition, recent results indicate that other PTS1-containing proteins interact with this same region of Pex5p in a similar way (<bold>K. Fodor, personal communication</bold>). Therefore, factors additional to the ancillary interface may determine the contribution of this binding site to cargo recognition. Recent data indicate that human PTS1 sequences show a range of binding affinities to Pex5p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. It is not hard to imagine that proteins with a relatively low binding affinity may require additional contact sites, to improve their targeting, while those with a high binding affinity (such as SCP2) would not. The targeting of GFP-SKL to peroxisomes falls into the last category. GFP (being a non-native import substrate commonly used as a reporter) is not expected to interact with the secondary interface in Pex5p, yet it is still efficiently targeted, indicating that SKL is sufficient to allow targeting in the absence of a secondary interface. Consequently, further data on other PTS1 cargo proteins are required, to provide insights into the role of the ancillary interface in peroxisome translocation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The data presented in this study clarify that the mechanism of SCP2 sorting to the peroxisome is absolutely PTS1 dependent but independent of the ancillary interface. It remains to be seen if a broad set of proteins destined for the peroxisome lumen utilise this ancillary binding site, or if the majority rely on a more rugged "PTS1 or nothing" selection, as appears to be the case here.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>Unless otherwise stated, all chemicals were obtained at the highest available purity from Sigma-Aldrich. Restriction enzymes were purchased from New England Biolabs (Ipswich, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Plasmids and cloning</title><p><italic>E. coli </italic>expression vectors for the production of human Pex5p(C) (spanning residues 315-639), preSCP2 (1-143) and mSCP2 (21-143) complete with N-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-GST fusion, cleavable with tobacco etch virus (TEV) protease have been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Primers described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] were also used to facilitate insertion of the four SCP2 variants (preSCP2 (1-143), mSCP2 (21-143), preSCP2&#x00394;AKL (1-140) and mSCP2&#x00394;AKL (21-140)) into pPC97 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] between <italic>Sal</italic>I and <italic>Not</italic>I, to generate fusions with Gal4 DNA binding domain (Gal4DB) for yeast two-hybrid analysis. The fusion of HsPex5p(C) and the Gal4 activation domain (Gal4AD) was made by cloning the <italic>Nco</italic>I-<italic>Not</italic>I fragment from the HsPex5p(C) <italic>E. coli </italic>expression vector into pPC97. Point mutations were introduced into the various Pex5p constructs using the QuikChange&#x02122; site directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene) using either the Gal4AD Pex5p(C) plasmid, the His<sub>6</sub>-GST Pex5p(C) plasmid, or the pcDNA3 derived expression vector pGD106 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] as templates. Details of the primers used can be seen in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>. The Pex5p S600W mutant has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. All constructs were confirmed by DNA sequencing.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>PCR primers used in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Primer name</th><th align="left">5'-3' sequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>HsPex5p: R608Wf</bold></td><td align="left">CATCTGGAGCACCCTGTGGTTGGCATTGTCTATGTTAGG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>HsPex5p: R608Wr</bold></td><td align="left">CCTAACATAGACAATGCCAACCACAGGGTGCTCCAGATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>HsPex5p: D624Wf</bold></td><td align="left">CCTATGGGGCAGCCTGGGCGCGGGATCTGTC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>HsPex5p: D624Wr</bold></td><td align="left">GACAGATCCCGCGCCCAGGCTGCCCCATAGG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Strains and culture conditions</title><p>Recombinant production of human Pex5p(C), preSCP2 and mSCP2 in <italic>E. coli </italic>has been described before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The yeast strain <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>PCY2 (<italic>MAT&#x00394;, &#x00394;gal4, &#x00394;gal80, URA3::GAL1-lacZ, lys2-801, his3-&#x00394;200, trp1-&#x00394;63, leu2, ade2-101</italic>) was used for two-hybrid analysis. Yeast transformations were performed as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Transformants were grown on minimal medium containing 0.67% yeast nitrogen base (Difco), 2% glucose and amino acids (20 &#x003bc;g/ml) as required.</p></sec><sec><title>Yeast two-hybrid analysis and Western blotting</title><p>GAL4 based yeast two hybrid analysis was conducted as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] with &#x003b2;-galactosidase enzyme activity determination being performed as in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Samples of lysates taken from the &#x003b2;-galactosidase assay were analysed by Western blotting for human Pex5p expression levels. Proteins were separated on a SDS-polyacrylamide gel and blotted onto a nitrocellulose membrane using a semi-dry system. Antibodies used were directed against <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>hexokinase (generous gift of H. van der Spek, FNWI, Amsterdam, The Netherlands) and human Pex5p described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] Antibody binding was detected with secondary antibodies labeled with IRDye 680 infrared dye on an Odyssey imager (LI-COR Biosciences).</p></sec><sec><title>Protein preparation and biotinylation</title><p>Preparation of Pex5p(C), preSCP2 and mSCP2 has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Mutant Pex5p(C) proteins were prepared in a similar way as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Purity was monitored by SDS-PAGE and mass spectrometry. For concentration determination, proteins were denatured in 8 M urea and the A<sub>280 nm </sub>was measured. Extinction coefficients were calculated using the method of Gill and von Hippel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Pex5p(C) wild-type and mutants were biotinylated using the EZ-Link<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>Sulfo-NHS-Biotinylation Kit (Pierce) as described by the manufacturer. Using the 4'-hydroxyazobenzene-2-carboxylic acid/avidin method, between 1 and 2 moles of biotin were found incorporated with 1 mole of Pex5p(C).</p></sec><sec><title>Isothermal titration microcalorimetry (ITC)</title><p>ITC was performed as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Measurements were conducted using a MicroCal VP-ITC using either wild-type or mutant (R608W or D624W) forms of Pex5p(C) titrated with either mSCP2 or a peptide derived from the C-terminus of SCP2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The peptide, PGNAKL, was synthesised by Sigma-Aldrich at &#x0003e; 95% purity.</p></sec><sec><title>Circular dichroism spectropolarimetry</title><p>Circular dichroism spectropolarimetry (CD) was performed as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] with Pex5p(C) at a concentration of 2 - 5 &#x003bc;M in 10 mM Potassium Phosphate buffer pH 7.4. Each spectrum presented is the average of three measurements. Standard deviations in ellipticity are shown with error bars. Spectra were background subtracted and helical content estimated via the DICHROWEB interface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], using CDSSTR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] with the SP175 basis set of spectra.</p></sec><sec><title>Static light scattering</title><p>The procedure used for static light scattering (SLS) analysis is described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Octet RED96 kinetic assays</title><p>To assess the binding kinetics of Pex5p(C) wild-type and point mutants to the four SCP2 variants, the Octet RED96 instrument (ForteBio) was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. All steps were carried out in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) at a rotation rate of 1000 rpm. Streptavidin conjugated sensors were hydrated for 10 minutes prior to use. The biotinylated sample proteins were immobilised onto the sensor at a concentration of 20 &#x003bc;g/mL. The experiment proceeded as follows; baseline - 60 seconds, biotinylated-sample loading - 300 seconds, baseline 2 - 60 seconds, association - 1800 seconds and dissociation - 1800 seconds. Data were acquired and assessed using the custom ForteBio software Data Acquisition v6.2 and Data Analysis v6.3. The data were processed with the Savitzky-Golay filter prior to analysis. Lines of best fit were generated locally based on a 1:1 model to determine the relative binding kinetics.</p></sec><sec><title>In vivo peroxisome import assays</title><p>Culturing and transfection of the Pex5p deficient human skin fibroblast cells for Zellweger syndrome patient PBD005 was performed as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. 12, 24 and 48 hours after transfection, cells were fixed onto cover glasses with 3% formaldehyde in PBS, permeablised with 1% Triton X-100 in PBS and subjected to immunofluorescence microscopy. To test for temperature-sensitive import defects, the temperature of cell culture was shifted from 37 to 40&#x000b0;C for 2 days. Polyclonal rabbit antibodies directed against human Pex14p are described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Polyclonal rabbit anti-Pex5p antibodies were raised against recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged Pex5p expressed in <italic>E. coli </italic>and purified as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Secondary antibodies were conjugated with Alexa Fluor 594 (Invitrogen). Samples were also inspected for GFP fluorescence. All micrographs were recorded on a Zeiss Axioplan 2 microscope with a Zeiss Plan-Apochromat 63x/1.4 oil objective and an Axiocam MR digital camera and were processed with AxioVision 4.2 software (Zeiss).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p><bold>CD</bold>: Circular dichroism spectropolarimetry; <bold>GFP</bold>: green fluorescent protein; <bold>ITC</bold>: isothermal titration calorimetry; <bold>PBS</bold>: phosphate buffered saline; <bold>PTS</bold>: peroxisomal targeting signal; <bold>SCP2</bold>: sterol carrier protein 2; <bold>SLS</bold>: Static light scattering; <bold>TPR</bold>: tetratricopeptide repeat.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>Experimental data were collected and analysed by CPW, NS, CAT, MvdB, SDvH, CSB, WS and WAS. The study was conceived and designed by CPW, RE, WS, MW and WAS. CPW, NS, CAT, RE, CSB, BD, WS, MW and WAS interpreted the data and prepared the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Krisztian Fodor for sharing unpublished results, Lise Hafkenscheid &#x00026; Matt Groves for technical assistance and other members of our labs for stimulating discussions. This work was partly funded by a grant from the Academic Medical Center awarded to B.D., a Rubicon Fellowship (825.08.023) from the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) awarded to C.P.W and by 3D-REPERTOIRE (EC, LSHG-CT-2005512028), grant awarded to M.W.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girzalsky</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Platta</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Protein transport across the peroxisomal membrane</article-title><source>Biol Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>390</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/BC.2009.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19558328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanyon-Hogg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Warriner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Getting a camel through the eye of a needle: the import of folded proteins by peroxisomes</article-title><source>Biol Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BC20090159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Geisbrecht</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Peroxisomal targeting signal-1 recognition by the TPR domains of human PEX5</article-title><source>Nat Struct Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/81930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipp</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kursula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliebs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Recognition of a functional peroxisome type 1 target by the dynamic import receptor pex5p</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2006.10.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17157249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pursiainen</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Garman</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Juffer</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kursula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>A previously unobserved conformation for the human Pex5p receptor suggests roles for intrinsic flexibility and rigid domain motions in ligand binding</article-title><source>BMC Struct Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6807-7-24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17428317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Optical biosensors: where next and how soon?</article-title><source>Drug Discov Today</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><issue>23-24</issue><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2006.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17129824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimozawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Osumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Orii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanders</surname><given-names>RJA</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Functional heterogeneity of C-terminal peroxisome targeting signal 1 in PEX5-defective patients</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>1999</year><volume>262</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1999.1232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10462504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>A proteome-wide perspective on peroxisome targeting signal 1(PTS1)-Pex5p affinities</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><volume>132</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3973</fpage><lpage>3979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja9109049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20178365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Versluis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Investigation of the ligand spectrum of human sterol carrier protein 2 using a direct mass spectrometry assay</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>2007</year><volume>461</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2007.02.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17418802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chevray</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathans</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Protein interaction cloning in yeast: identification of mammalian proteins that react with the leucine zipper of Jun</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1992</year><volume>89</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>5789</fpage><lpage>5793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.89.13.5789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1631061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Braverman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>An isoform of pex5p, the human PTS1 receptor, is required for the import of PTS2 proteins into peroxisomes</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/7.8.1195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9668159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van der Leij</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Franse</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elgersma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><article-title>PAS10 is a tetratricopeptide-repeat protein that is essential for the import of most matrix proteins into peroxisomes of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>11782</fpage><lpage>11786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.24.11782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8265627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Konings</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Recognition of peroxisomal targeting signal type 1 by the import receptor Pex5p</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>15034</fpage><lpage>15041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M010776200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schliebs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidowsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Agianian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Herberg</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><article-title>Recombinant human peroxisomal targeting signal receptor PEX5. Structural basis for interaction of PEX5 with PEX14</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5666</fpage><lpage>5673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.9.5666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10026185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><article-title>Calculation of protein extinction coefficients from amino acid sequence data</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1989</year><volume>182</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(89)90602-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2610349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Opalinski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenhuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Klei</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><article-title>Membrane curvature during peroxisome fission requires Pex11</article-title><source>Embo J</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2010.299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21113128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Protein secondary structure analyses from circular dichroism spectroscopy: methods and reference databases</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2008</year><volume>89</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bip.20853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17896349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sreerama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Woody</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><article-title>Estimation of protein secondary structure from circular dichroism spectra: comparison of CONTIN, SELCON, and CDSSTR methods with an expanded reference set</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abio.2000.4880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11112271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nettleship</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Geerlof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Methods for protein characterization by mass spectrometry, thermal shift (ThermoFluor) assay, and multiangle or static light scattering</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>426</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><comment>full_text</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18542872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Soukupova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunau</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Identification and characterization of the human orthologue of yeast Pex14p</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2265</fpage><lpage>2277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10022913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuttelkopf</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><article-title>ALINE: a WYSIWYG protein-sequence alignment editor for publication-quality alignments</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><issue>Pt 5</issue><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909007835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Dictionary of Protein Secondary Structure - Pattern-Recognition of Hydrogen-Bonded and Geometrical Features</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1983</year><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2577</fpage><lpage>2637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bip.360221211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6667333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>