<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Biochem</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Biochemistry</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2091</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2631452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2091-10-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121228</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2091-10-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Redox biology of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv: protein-protein interaction between GlgB and WhiB1 involves exchange of thiol-disulfide</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>Saurabh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gargs@ebs.ogi.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>Md Suhail</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>suhail@imtech.res.in</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bajpai</surname><given-names>Richa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>richa@imtech.res.in</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kishan</surname><given-names>KV Radha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>radhakishan@gvkbio.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Pushpa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>pushpa@imtech.res.in</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Environmental and Biomolecular Systems, OGI School of Science and Engineering, Oregon Health and Science University, 20000 NW Walker Road, Beaverton, Oregon, 97006, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institute of Microbial Technology, CSIR, Sector-39A, Chandigarh, 160036, India</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Informatics, GVK Biosciences, Hyderabad, 500037, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2091/10/1"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Garg et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Garg et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Garg
               Saurabh
               
               gargs@ebs.ogi.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Redox biology of Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Rv: protein-protein interaction between GlgB and WhiB1 involves exchange of thiol-disulfide
         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Biochemistry 10(1): 1-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2091(2009)10:1&#x0003c;1&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2091</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, an intracellular pathogen encounters redox stress throughout its life inside the host. In order to protect itself from the redox onslaughts of host immune system, <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>appears to have developed accessory thioredoxin-like proteins which are represented by ORFs encoding WhiB-like proteins. We have earlier reported that WhiB1/Rv3219 is a thioredoxin like protein of <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>and functions as a protein disulfide reductase. Generally thioredoxins have many substrate proteins. The current study aims to identify the substrate protein(s) of <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>WhiB1.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Using yeast two-hybrid screen, we identified alpha (1,4)-glucan branching enzyme (GlgB) of <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>as a interaction partner of WhiB1. <italic>In vitro </italic>GST pull down assay confirmed the direct physical interaction between GlgB and WhiB1. Both mass spectrometry data of tryptic digests and <italic>in vitro </italic>labeling of cysteine residues with 4-acetamido-4' maleimidyl-stilbene-2, 2'-disulfonic acid showed that in GlgB, C<sup>95 </sup>and C<sup>658 </sup>are free but C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>form an intra-molecular disulfide bond. WhiB1 has a C<sup>37</sup>XXC<sup>40 </sup>motif thus a C<sup>40</sup>S mutation renders C<sup>37 </sup>to exist as a free thiol to form a hetero-disulfide bond with the cysteine residue of substrate protein. A disulfide mediated binary complex formation between GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S was shown by both in-solution protein-protein interaction and thioredoxin affinity chromatography. Finally, transfer of reducing equivalent from WhiB1 to GlgB disulfide was confirmed by 4-acetamido-4' maleimidyl-stilbene-2, 2'-disulfonic acid trapping by the reduced disulfide of GlgB. Two different thioredoxins, TrxB/Rv1471 and TrxC/Rv3914 of <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>could not perform this reaction suggesting that the reduction of GlgB by WhiB1 is specific.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We conclude that <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>GlgB has one intra-molecular disulfide bond which is formed between C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617</sup>. WhiB1, a thioredoxin like protein interacts with GlgB and transfers its electrons to the disulfide thus reduces the intra-molecular disulfide bond of GlgB. For the first time, we report that GlgB is one of the <italic>in vivo </italic>substrate of <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>WhiB1.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>A large number of cellular processes are mediated through protein-protein interactions. In general, these interactions are non-covalent and are outcome of hydrophobic or ionic or both interactions. In case of thioredoxin (Trx), a protein-protein interaction is followed by the exchange of disulfide from thioredoxin to the substrate protein. Trx is a major protein disulfide reductase responsible for maintaining the redox state of cytosol. They are involved in large number of cell processes and regulate the activity of many proteins through reversible reduction of their disulfide bonds. The specificity of a Trx towards its target is determined by the local environment around its active site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Thioredoxins (Trxs) take electrons for their reduction from NADPH <italic>via </italic>thioredoxin reductase and then transfer them to target disulfide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]; hence, they play a key role in a cell's defense against oxidative stress. Trxs have a universal folding pattern known as 'thioredoxin fold' and a conserved but solvent exposed CXXC motif, as an active site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In <italic>E</italic>.<italic>coli</italic>, Trxs are also involved in the reduction of disulfide bonds of OxyR, Hsp33 <italic>etc</italic>. and regulate their biochemical function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. They often regenerate cellular proteins by reducing non-specific disulfides formed during oxidative stress thus also function as an important antioxidant system. In eukaryotes, Trxs regulate activity of transcription factors NF-&#x003ba;B and AP-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The activation of peroxiredoxins, which facilitates reduction of reactive oxygen species, is dependent on Trxs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Alpha (1,4)-glucan branching enzyme (GlgB) of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>(<italic>Mtb</italic>) is encoded by Rv1326c [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Earlier, we have reported that the recombinant protein produced by Rv1326c is functionally active [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Amino acids sequence analysis showed that both <italic>Mtb </italic>and <italic>M. bovis </italic>GlgB has four cysteine residues (in <italic>Mtb </italic>these are C<sup>95</sup>, C<sup>193</sup>, C<sup>617</sup>and C<sup>658</sup>) but are absent in other mycobacteria. We indicated that cysteine residues of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB may form intra-molecular disulfide bond(s) and its reduction leads to a conformational change of the protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. High density transposon mutagenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] showed that <italic>glgB </italic>gene is essential for the optimal growth of <italic>Mtb in vitro</italic>, suggesting that it is an important gene. However, its importance in physiology of <italic>Mtb </italic>has not yet been established. <italic>Mtb </italic>has three different pathways for trehalose biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] where GlgB is likely to be a part of one of the pathways. Glycogen is a mixture of glucose polymers, thus GlgB may help in the synthesis of a precursor for trehalose biosynthesis. Both in mycobacteria and corynebacteria, trehalose is a basic component of a number of cell wall glycolipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], cord factor (trehalose 6,6'-dimycolate), sulpholipids (acetylated trehalose-2'-sulphate derivatives) and trehalose containing lipo-oligosaccharides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Lately, enzymes of trehalose biosynthetic pathways have gained major attention as drug targets especially in mycobacteria, as capsular polysaccharides of <italic>Mtb </italic>have been found to modulate the host immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>In <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor </italic>A3(2), <italic>whiB </italic>gene was shown to be associated with sporulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. <italic>Mtb </italic>does not sporulate but has seven ORFs which are orthologues of <italic>whiB </italic>of <italic>S. coelicolor </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The presence of multiple <italic>whiB </italic>genes in <italic>M. leprae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and the growing body of evidence that these genes are involved in cell division, oxidative stress, antibiotic resistance, pathogenesis <italic>etc. </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], suggests that these genes are likely to have functional significance in mycobacteria. Amino acid sequence analysis of WhiB proteins showed that they all have four conserved cysteines. Except in WhiB5/Rv0022c of <italic>Mtb</italic>, which has a CXXXC motif, all other WhiB proteins have a CXXC motif which is similar to thioredoxins and other oxidoreductases. In mycobacteria, ORFs showing sequence similarities to <italic>whiB </italic>are annotated as putative transcription factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. However, so far the molecular function of WhiB proteins as a DNA binding proteins has not been established. We have reported that WhiB proteins, except WhiB2, have properties similar to thioredoxin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] suggesting that these proteins would function <italic>via </italic>protein-protein interaction. Interaction of thioredoxins with substrate protein involves exchange of thiol-disulfide. However, occasionally thioredoxins also regulate the activity of the cognate protein independent of disulfide exchange [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p><p>In the present study, we show that WhiB1 and GlgB of <italic>Mtb </italic>exchange their thiol disulfide. Initially, GlgB was identified as a possible substrate protein of WhiB1 in a yeast two-hybrid screen. Physical interaction between the two proteins was confirmed by GST pull-down assay. The data obtained from the mass spectrometry and 4-acetamido-4' maleimidyl-stilbene-2, 2'-disulfonic acid (AMS) trapping confirmed that an intra-molecular disulfide bond is formed between C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB. Using a series of biochemical methods; we suggest that GlgB is a substrate of WhiB1.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>WhiB1 interacts with GlgB</title><p>WhiB1, a thioredoxin like protein is likely to function <italic>via </italic>protein-protein interaction therefore, yeast two-hybrid system was employed to identify the potential interacting partner/s of WhiB1. The suitability of yeast two-hybrid system to study mycobacterial protein-protein interaction has been well demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>The expression of <italic>whiB</italic>1 (fused to DNA binding domain of Gal4p, pDBD-B1) was studied by repression assay where the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-galactosidase (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal) activity of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>cells transformed with vector pJK101 and pDBD-B1 was measured. In yeast two-hybrid analysis, when bait is expressed and binds to the LexA operator region, the expression of downstream reporter gene (<italic>lacZ </italic>in this study) is repressed. The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal expression was significantly repressed in the cells transformed with pDBD-B1 whereas, the transformants lacking bait showed increased <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal expression (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The data clearly suggested that the WhiB1 expressed in the yeast cell and was able to bind to the operator region. The intrinsic transcription activation of bait was ruled out by testing the expression of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>transformed by constructs: pSH18-34 + pJG4-5 + pDBD-B1. Transformants containing: pSH18-34 + pJG4-5 + pSH17-4 and pSH18-34 + pJG4-5+ pRFHM1 were used as positive and negative controls, respectively. Absence of blue color in the test transformants clones (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, panel 1) similar to the negative control clones (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, panel 3) confirmed that WhiB1 lack intrinsic transcription activation property and was suitable to be used in yeast two-hybrid analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Yeast two-hybrid analysis using <italic>whiB</italic>1 as 'bait'</bold>. <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>cells were transformed with plasmids: pDBD-B1 (bait), pAD<italic>Mtb </italic>(prey) and pSH18-34 (reporter plasmid) and the transformants were selected on Glu<sup>+</sup>His<sup>-</sup>Ura<sup>-</sup>Trp<sup>- </sup>plates. The transformants were pooled and allowed to grow in a liquid medium supplemented with galactose (1%) for 6 h at 30&#x000b0;C in order to induce the expression of gene cloned in pAD<italic>Mtb</italic>. After induction, the cells were plated on Gal<sup>+</sup>His<sup>-</sup>Ura<sup>-</sup>Trp<sup>- </sup>Leu<sup>- </sup>plates. Viable clones were further tested for specific interaction by dilution plating on Gal<sup>+</sup>His<sup>-</sup>Ura<sup>-</sup>Trp<sup>-</sup>Leu<sup>- </sup>and Glu<sup>+</sup>His<sup>-</sup>Ura<sup>-</sup>Trp<sup>-</sup>Leu<sup>- </sup>plates. Growth of two representative positive clones in dilution plating is shown in the picture. Figures on the top indicate the total number of cells spotted on the respective plate for dilution plating.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-1"/></fig><p>To search for an interaction partner, <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>cells were transformed with pDBD-B1 (bait) and the genomic library of <italic>Mtb </italic>H37Rv, which was created as a fusion to the activation domain (pAD<italic>Mtb</italic>) of Gal4P. The system used in this study is based upon the transcription of a reporter gene which occurs when the two separately expressed domains of Gal4p physically interact. Therefore, when the two proteins are expressed as a fusion to two different domains of Gal4p, their physical interaction leads to functional reconstitution of Gal4p thereby leading to the activation of expression of reporter genes, <italic>LEU</italic>2 or <italic>lacZ</italic>, when grown in a medium containing galactose but not glucose. At the end of the screening process, we obtained sixteen clones exclusively growing on galactose medium in the absence of leucine (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Among all, 15 clones had an in-frame fusion with 596 bp 3' end of ORF Rv1326c/<italic>glgB </italic>whereas one was false positive (vector sequence alone).</p><p>Results obtained by yeast-two hybrid analysis were further confirmed by GST pull-down assay. WhiB1 and WhiB4 proteins were expressed as a fusion to GST (pGEX-B1 and pGEX-B4). Both, pGEX-B1 and pGEX-B4 (control) were co-expressed separately with pETgl (full length <italic>glgB </italic>cloned in pET29a to express it as a C-terminus 6-&#x000d7; His tagged fusion protein). The proteins were immobilized on glutathione sepharose resin. The absence of GlgB in lanes: GST alone and WhiB4-GST (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) suggested that the interaction between WhiB1 and GlgB is specific. It is evident from the Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> that WhiB1 interacts with GlgB but not with WhiB4 or GST alone, suggesting that the interaction of GlgB and WhiB1 is specific. In the pull down assay a ~27 kDa protein was co-eluted. N-terminal amino acids sequencing of this protein identified it as a cleaved GST.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>WhiB1 physically interacts with GlgB <italic>in vitro</italic></bold>. GST pull down assay to show GlgB interacts with WhiB1. WhiB1-GST/WhiB4-GST/GST-alone were co-expressed with GlgB-6&#x000d7; His in <italic>E. coli </italic>BL21(DE3). Interaction was carried out using glutathione agarose beads as described in 'materials and methods'. The left panel is 10% SDS-PAGE stained with silver nitrate, whereas the right panel is an immuno-blot showing the co-elution of GlgB along with WhiB1-GST. The asterisks denote the position of WhiB4-GST (*), WhiB1-GST (**) and GST-alone (***).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-2"/></fig><p>The interaction data was surprising because to the best of our knowledge, interaction of a Trx-like protein with an enzyme of sugar metabolic pathway has not been reported in any microorganism except cyanobacteria. Amino acids sequence analysis of GlgBs from different organisms showed that except <italic>Mtb </italic>and <italic>M. bovis</italic>, no other GlgB has four cysteine residues. Earlier, we have reported that <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB has at least one intra-molecular disulfide bond [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Therefore, we investigated the number and arrangement of intra-molecular disulfide bond(s) in GlgB.</p></sec><sec><title>C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>of GlgB form an intra-molecular disulfide bond</title><p>The peptide mass finger printing analysis of tryptic digests of cysteine alkylated and non alkylated GlgB showed that both C<sup>95 </sup>(LQVTVEG<bold><underline>C</underline></bold>EPHTVADAYR) and C<sup>658 </sup>(VGSDGSVLA<bold><underline>C</underline></bold>VFNFAGAEHR) were alkylated under oxidizing conditions suggesting that these two cysteine residues were free and surface exposed (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), while peptides containing either C<sup>193 </sup>or C<sup>617 </sup>could not be detected. Surprisingly, we could not detect the peptide containing C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>even under normal reducing conditions. However, incubation of reduced GlgB at 45&#x000b0;C followed by alkylation and trypsin digestion resulted in to the detection of peptide (<bold><underline>C</underline></bold>HPALWSLDTTPEGYSWIDANDSANNVLSFMR) containing C<sup>617</sup>(Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>) but not the peptide (VLGPSGVWELFWPDFP<bold><underline>C</underline></bold>DGLYK) containing C<sup>193</sup>. The result indicated that under normal reducing conditions, the peptide with C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>might be buried and was not accessible to trypsin, whereas at 45&#x000b0;C, possibly a change in conformation led to the exposure of an internal trypsin recognition site which released the peptide with C<sup>617 </sup>but not the peptide stretch containing C<sup>193</sup>. Based upon our earlier report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and the present mass spectrometry data, we propose that an intra-molecular disulfide bond is formed between C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617</sup>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Peptide mass fingerprinting of GlgB</bold>. DTT treated and untreated GlgB was alkylated, digested with trypsin and precipitated with TCA. The molecular mass of the peptides were analyzed by MALDI-TOF. (A) Peptide mass spectra highlighting the molecular mass of peptide containing C<sup>95 </sup>and C<sup>658 </sup>(marked with arrow) under oxidizing conditions. (B) Peptide mass spectra under reducing conditions. The molecular mass of the peptides containing cysteines (as labeled) were similar to the peptide obtained under oxidized conditions, confirming that both C<sup>95 </sup>and C<sup>658 </sup>are free and surface exposed. (C) Peptide mass spectra of GlgB pre-incubated at 45&#x000b0;C before reduction, alkylation and trypsinization. Peptide containing C<sup>617 </sup>is marked with an arrow; however C<sup>193 </sup>could not be detected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-3"/></fig><p>In order to know about the domain organization in <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB, a structure model was generated (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) using the structure of <italic>E. coli </italic>GlgB as a template (the proteins shares 48% sequence identity and 68% similarity). The <italic>E. coli </italic>GlgB structure was determined without one of the N-terminal domains (N1) because of crystallization related problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. The <italic>E. coli </italic>GlgB contains three laterally arranged domains <italic>i.e</italic>. N2, catalytic (TIM-barrel) and the C-terminal domains. The relative orientation and function of the N1 domain is not yet known and it is assumed that it possibly regulates the size of sugar branching during glycogen synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. The model indicated that <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB is also likely to have four domains. Interestingly, each of the domains of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB has one cysteine residue (C<sup>95 </sup>in N1, C<sup>193 </sup>in N2, C<sup>617 </sup>in active site and C<sup>658 </sup>in C-terminus). It appears that an intra-molecular disulfide bond may link the N2 and catalytic domains and after reduction, the two domains would have separated which exposed the C<sup>617 </sup>while the N2 domain, especially the region containing C<sup>193 </sup>might have got re-oriented therefore was not accessible for trypsinization. This could be a possible reason why the peptide containing C<sup>193 </sup>was not detected in mass spectrometry. Based upon the mass spectrometry data and structural model, a possible scheme of domains organization in oxidized GlgB has been depicted in the Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Possible domain organization of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB</bold>. The schematic arrangement of the four domains of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB is based on mass spectrometric data and structure model. Cysteines (C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617</sup>) of GlgB which form an intra-molecular disulfide bond are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>WhiB1 and GlgB interaction involves exchange of thiol-disulfide</title><p>To prove the hypothesis that interaction of WhiB1 with GlgB may involve exchange of thiol-disulfide, the Trx affinity chromatography method, originally developed by Motohashi <italic>et al. </italic>(2001) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] was employed. First of all, a WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S mutant was generated, which rendered C<sup>37 </sup>to remain as a thiolate ion. To demonstrate the formation of hetero-disulfide bond between GlgB and WhiB1, purified WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S or WhiB1WT (control) proteins were covalently immobilized on CNBr activated sepharose resin. Both C<sup>95 </sup>and C<sup>658 </sup>of GlgB were alkylated under oxidizing condition to prevent a non-specific reaction between free thiols of GlgB and C<sup>37 </sup>of WhiB1. Interaction was initiated by mixing immobilized WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S and pre-alkylated oxidized GlgB. The reaction was terminated at different time points and samples were resolved by non-reducing PAGE. The Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> clearly shows that GlgB formed a complex with WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S just after 10 minutes of interaction unlike WhiB1WT where GlgB was washed out completely in high salt buffer. The result indicated that a binary complex formed between GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S was stabilized by a hetero-disulfide bond.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Thioredoxin affinity chromatography</bold>. (A) Immuno-blot after thioredoxin affinity chromatography to show that the binary complex between GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S was destabilized by DTT. Panels: (1) interaction of GlgB with WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S, (2) interaction of GlgB with WhiB1WT. (B) In-solution protein-protein interaction to show the formation of a binary complex between GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S. After reactions, the samples were resolved by 8&#x02013;18% step gradient SDS-PAGE and stained with coomassie blue. A binary complex between WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S and GlgB at ~97 kDa marker position (lanes 3 &#x00026; 4) disappeared when <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ME was added (lanes 12 &#x00026; 13). Rests of the lanes are controls as labeled. The triangles represent the interaction carried out using two different concentrations of WhiB1 and GlgB (5 or 10 &#x003bc;M of each protein).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-5"/></fig><p>In Trx affinity chromatography, the binary complex formed between the two proteins is not released because WhiB1/WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S is covalently bound to the resin. In order to demonstrate that GlgB and WhiB1 are indeed linked by a hetero-disulfide bond, purified pre-alkylated oxidized GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S were incubated together in the interaction buffer. The reaction was terminated at different time points and the samples were resolved by SDS-PAGE. A higher molecular weight protein band (~97 kDa) along with the two input bands of GlgB (~85 kDa) and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S (~14 kDa), was clearly visible (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, lanes 3 &#x00026; 4). The ~97 kDa protein band corresponded to the combined sizes of GlgB: WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S binary complex which disappeared when 1% <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ME was added to the sample (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, lanes 12 &#x00026; 13), thus confirming the formation of an inter-molecular hetero-disulfide bond between GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S. As expected, the ~97 kDa band was missing in the GlgB: WhiB1WT control sample (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, lanes 7 &#x00026; 8) because the intact CXXC motif of WhiB1WT could not form a stable inter-molecular hetero-disulfide bond with GlgB.</p><p>The direct evidence for the reduction of GlgB disulfide by WhiB1 was shown using AMS trapping method. The fluorescent dye, AMS, absorbs light at 322 nm and emits at 411 nm. Binding of each molecule of AMS also increases the mass of a protein by ~500 Da. Thus, AMS labeled proteins fluoresce under UV light and show reduced mobility on SDS-PAGE. Purified <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB was pre-alkylated under oxidizing condition with iodoacetamide (IAA) to block the free cysteines thus AMS binding would occur if C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>are free either due to the reduction by WhiB1 or DTT or by other Trx-like proteins. The AMS treatment of oxidized and pre-alkylated GlgB did not show any fluorescence or mobility shift (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, lane 2), suggesting that the free cysteines were successfully alkylated. Pre-alkylated GlgB when reduced by DTT and then labeled with AMS fluoresced under UV light and also showed mobility shift (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, lane 3). Similarly, when pre-alkylated GlgB was incubated with pre-reduced WhiB1 and labeled with AMS, it fluoresced under UV light and showed mobility shift on the gel (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, lane 6). However, pre-alkylated GlgB incubated with oxidized WhiB1 and then labeled with AMS failed to fluoresce and also did not show any mobility shift (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, lane 5). Together, these data suggested that WhiB1 converted the disulfide of GlgB into reduced thiol, to which AMS reacted covalently. In order to know whether GlgB's disulfide could be reduced by other Trxs of <italic>Mtb</italic>; TrxB and TrxC of <italic>Mtb </italic>were cloned, expressed and proteins were purified (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Both, TrxB and TrxC catalyzed the reduction of insulin disulfides by DTT suggesting that the proteins were in native conformation and enzymatically active (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, Table 1). However, incubation of GlgB with either reduced WhiB4 or TrxB or TrxC did not show AMS labeling of GlgB (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, lane 7&#x02013;9). The data clearly suggested that the transfer of reducing equivalents from WhiB1 to GlgB is a highly specific reaction, as its absence could not be compensated either by known Trxs or WhiB4 of <italic>Mtb</italic>. The result also confirmed that C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617 </sup>of GlgB form an intra-molecular disulfide bond.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Reduction of GlgB's disulfide by reduced WhiB1</bold>. After interaction between WhiB1 and GlgB, the reduced cysteines of GlgB were trapped using AMS and the samples were resolved by 8% SDS-PAGE. Panels are: (1) resolved GlgB on gel, as visualized under UV light, the fluorescent band shows the binding of AMS to reduced cysteines of GlgB as labeled, (2) coomassie stained gel (after photographed under UV light) to show the presence of GlgB. The AMS labeled GlgB also showed mobility shift. Lanes are indicated on the top.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>WhiB1 promoter activates at late stationary phase</title><p>For a successful interaction between two proteins, it is essential that both are present in the cytosol at the same time. The glycogen synthesis in <italic>S. coelicolor </italic>A3(2) has been shown to be associated with sporulation which represent stationary phase of the growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. In order to determine the stage when <italic>whiB</italic>1 is expressed, the upstream regulatory sequence of <italic>whiB</italic>1 was cloned upstream to the <italic>lacZ </italic>of a promoter less vector pJEM15 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The expression of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal was monitored at different stages of growth. For the first 24 h, the expression was at the basal level. However, it induced after 48 h of growth and increased suddenly by 72 h (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). The increase in <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal activity continued up to 120 h and saturated afterwards, suggesting that the <italic>whiB</italic>1 expression is likely to be at the late stationary phase of the growth. Increased level of <italic>whiB</italic>1 transcripts in stationary phase has also been demonstrated by RT-PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that interaction between GlgB and WhiB1 is a stationary phase phenomenon.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Growth phase dependent activation of putative <italic>Mtb whiB</italic>1 promoter in <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>mc2155</bold>. <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>cells carrying pJEM15 (vector control, white bar) or <italic>pwhiB</italic>1<italic>-lacZ </italic>(grey bar) were aerobically grown for different periods as indicated. Cells were aliquoted at different time points (indicated as h, at the bottom of each bar) and <italic>A</italic><sub>600 </sub>was measured followed by the preparation of whole cell lysate. The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal activity was measured in standard 'Z' buffer. <italic>Inset</italic>: Growth curve of <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-7"/></fig><p>Interaction of GlgB with Trxs has been reported in chloroplast and <italic>Synechocystis sps. </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Although, a Trx-mediated post-translational regulation of GlgB in the photosynthetic organisms has been indicated but the biochemical evidence to this has not been demonstrated yet. Earlier, we have shown a redox mediated conformational change in <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that under oxidizing conditions (<italic>in vivo </italic>oxidative stress); an intra-molecular disulfide bond formed between C<sup>193 </sup>and C<sup>617</sup>. This would possibly bring a conformational change in GlgB which may introduce steric constrain thereby can affect the stability of the protein. Recently, WhiB1 has been demonstrated to co-ordinate an oxidation labile iron-sulfur cluster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. It appears that under oxidative stress and/or stationary phase (mild oxidative stress), WhiB1 transforms from inactive holo-form to active apo-form, interacts with GlgB and reduces its oxidized disulfide. WhiB1-mediated reduction of oxidized disulfide would possibly regenerate the GlgB by bringing back to sterically stable state. Therefore, the presence of sterically stable GlgB in stationary phase of the growth will be beneficial to cell where metabolism is usually very low thus, bacteria would avoid any excess consumption of ATP. However, at this juncture due to the lack of experimental evidence, it will be pre-mature to pinpoint the importance of GlgB: WhiB1 interaction and exchange of thiol-disulfide under <italic>in vivo </italic>conditions. Nevertheless, the results described in this study as well as the methods used, would certainly help in deducing many thiol mediated regulatory processes in <italic>Mtb</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The data described here show for the first time that GlgB, an enzyme of carbohydrate metabolism is a substrate of WhiB1, a Trx-like protein of <italic>Mtb</italic>. Since, the disulfide bond formation so far, appears to be unique to <italic>Mtb </italic>and may be to <italic>M. bovis </italic>also; both GlgB and WhiB1 are likely to have much more important role in these two species of mycobacteria than others. Although, in yeast-two hybrid analysis we found only GlgB as an interacting protein of WhiB1 however, it does not mean that WhiB1 will not interact with any other protein. Therefore, a detail analysis of protein-protein interaction between WhiB1 with other proteins of <italic>Mtb </italic>is required to understand entire network, which may exist during stationary phase. Further, it is also possible that interaction between WhiB1 and some other protein does not involve thiol-disulfide exchange because Trxs from other systems have been shown to act as structural components of other protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains and reagents</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli </italic>DH5&#x003b1; was used for general cloning procedures. Media components were purchase from Difco, USA. T4 DNA ligase was purchased from Promega (USA) while other restriction and DNA modifying enzymes were procured from New England Biolabs (USA). The primers were obtained from Biobasic, Inc. (Canada). Plasmid pET-29a and <italic>E. coli </italic>BL21(DE3) were purchased from Novagen (USA). Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA agarose resin and other PCR/plasmid purification kits were supplied by Qiagen (Germany). The EDTA free protease inhibitor cocktail was purchased from Roche, (Germany). All other fine chemicals and antibodies were procured either from Sigma (USA) or otherwise mentioned. Standard recombinant DNA techniques were followed as described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Cloning, expression and purification of recombinant proteins</title><p>Genomic DNA of <italic>Mtb </italic>was isolated using a method described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Cysteine to serine mutation of WhiB1 was generated by overlapping extension PCR using a primer pair consisting of wild type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] and appropriately mutated primer as mentioned in the Table 2 (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). Cloning, expression and purification procedures of mutant proteins were as described for WhiB1WT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Over-expression and purification of GlgB was carried out as described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] whereas, the expression and purification method of WhiB4 has been described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Both <italic>trx</italic>B/Rv1471 and <italic>trx</italic>C/Rv3914 of <italic>Mtb </italic>were PCR amplified from the genomic DNA using sequence specific primers (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, Table 2) and cloned into vector pET-29a at <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Xho</italic>I and <italic>Bam</italic>HI-<italic>Hind</italic>III sites, respectively. Proteins were over-expressed at 30&#x000b0;C by 0.5 mM IPTG for 3 h and purified using Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA affinity chromatography following manufacturer's instructions (Qiagen, Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>Yeast two-hybrid assay</title><p><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>EGY191 was used throughout in yeast two-hybrid analysis. 'Bait' and 'prey' fusions were constructed in pEG202 and pJG4-5, respectively as suggested by Golemis and Brent (1997) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. <italic>whiB</italic>1/Rv3219 was PCR amplified using gene specific primers (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>, Table 2) and <italic>Mtb </italic>genomic DNA as template. The gene was cloned at <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Xho</italic>I site of pEG202 to create pDBD-B1 (bait). Characterization of 'bait': (a) expression in yeast and (b) lack of intrinsic transcriptional activity, was carried out using the methods described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. The <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Xho</italic>I digested genomic DNA of <italic>Mtb </italic>were cloned at the same sites of pJG4-5 to express <italic>Mtb </italic>genomic library in fusion with the activation domain of acid blob under <italic>gal </italic>promoter (pAD<italic>Mtb</italic>) and was transformed into <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, along with the standard control vectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. The transformants were selected on respective drop out plates and tested for the activation of reporter genes <italic>i.e. LEU2 </italic>and <italic>lacZ</italic>. The selected clones were sequenced in an automated DNA sequencer (ABI 310) and analyzed by the 'Blastn' server (NCBI, NIH).</p></sec><sec><title>GST pull down assay</title><p>The PCR amplified fragments of <italic>whiB</italic>1 and <italic>whiB</italic>4/Rv3681c were cloned at <italic>EcoR</italic>I-<italic>Xho</italic>I sites of vector pGEX4T-1 to generate fusion plasmids pGEX-B1 and pGEX-B4, respectively. Both WhiB1 and WhiB4 (internal control) were expressed as N-terminus GST fusion proteins. The pET-gl and pGEX-B1 or pGEX-B4 was co-transformed in <italic>E. coli </italic>BL21 (DE3) cells and protein expression was induced by 0.5 mM IPTG for 3 h at 30&#x000b0;C. The harvested cells were re-suspended in 1 ml lysis buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA containing protease inhibitors cocktail. After one freeze-thaw cycle, lysozyme (2 mg/ml) was added, incubated for 1 h at 37&#x000b0;C and sonicated. The soluble cell lysate was separated by centrifugation at 17,000 g for 30 minutes. The crude lysate of co-expressing test proteins (500 &#x003bc;g) was mixed with 3 mg of pre-equilibrated glutathione agarose beads and the reaction was carried out in the pull-down buffer: 100 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1% Triton X-100, and 1 mM DTT, at 4&#x000b0;C for 3 h with continuous mixing. The beads were washed five times with 1 ml of pull-down buffer then mixed with gel loading buffer, boiled and the bound proteins were resolved on 10% SDS-PAGE. The gel was stained with silver nitrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Co-elution of GlgB and WhiB1 was confirmed by immuno-blot using anti-6&#x000d7;His tag monoclonal antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>Mass spectrometry</title><p>To investigate the presence of disulfide bond(s) in GlgB, 100 &#x003bc;g purified protein was incubated with 10 mM DTT for 1 h at 25&#x000b0;C. Both DTT treated and untreated proteins were incubated for 12 h with 20 mM IAA at 37&#x000b0;C in dark and then digested with 2 &#x003bc;g of proteomics grade trypsin for 10 h at 25&#x000b0;C. The digested proteins were precipitated by 10% trichloroacetic acid (TCA) for 15 minutes in ice, washed twice with chilled acetone, air dried and re-suspended in 0.1% TFA. Two &#x003bc;l of each protein sample was mixed with an equal volume of the matrix and mass spectra were recorded in Brukers, Ultraflex MALDI-TOF spectrometer. In another set of experiments, GlgB was incubated at 45&#x000b0;C for 4 h before DTT treatment, alkylated with IAA, digested with trypsin, precipitated by TCA and mass spectra were recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>Trx affinity chromatography</title><p>The Trx affinity chromatography method of Motohashi <italic>et al </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] was used to study the thiol-disulfide exchange between GlgB and WhiB1. WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S (5 mg) was immobilized on cyanogen bromide (CNBr) activated sepharose beads and was equilibrated with 5 column volumes of binding buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 0.05% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. To the equilibrated resin, 1 mg GlgB (oxidized and pre-alkylated with IAA was mixed and interaction was carried out at 25&#x000b0;C in the presence of protease inhibitor cocktail. Samples were removed every 10 minutes and washed with buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 0.5 M NaCl until the wash was free of any protein. The bound protein was eluted in 3 ml wash buffer supplemented with 10 mM DTT, precipitated by TCA and resolved by 10% SDS-PAGE. Immuno-blotting was carried out using monoclonal anti-6&#x000d7; His tag antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>Demonstration of hetero-disulfide linked binary complex formation by SDS-PAGE</title><p>GlgB and WhiB1C<sup>40</sup>S or WhiB1WT were mixed in equimolar concentrations (5 or 10 &#x003bc;M) in a buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 0.05% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA and 10 mM MgCl<sub>2 </sub>for 2 h at 25&#x000b0;C. After reaction, gel loading buffer with or without <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-mercaptoethanol (&#x003b2;-ME) was added to the samples, resolved by 8&#x02013;18% step gradient SDS-PAGE and were visualized by coomassie staining.</p></sec><sec><title>AMS trapping by reduced thiol of GlgB</title><p>WhiB1, WhiB4, TrxB and TrxC were reduced with 0.5 mM DTT in 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl for 1 h at 25&#x000b0;C. Transfer of reducing equivalents from reduced WhiB1 or other proteins (10 &#x003bc;M) to GlgB (5 &#x003bc;M) was studied by incubating them together in a reaction buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 0.05% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2 </sub>for 10 minutes at 25&#x000b0;C in a 50 &#x003bc;l reaction volume. The concentration of reduced WhiB1/other proteins were adjusted to achieve a final concentration of DTT to 0.02 mM in the reaction mixture because 0.02 mM DTT was not enough to reduce the amount of GlgB used in the present study. Oxidized GlgB and WhiB1 were incubated together with or without 0.02 mM DTT and were used as controls. WhiB4, TrxB and TrxC were also used as internal controls to test the specificity of interaction between GlgB and WhiB1. Reactions were stopped by adding 10% TCA. The proteins were precipitated, air dried, re-suspended in 10 &#x003bc;l 15 mM AMS (Molecular Probes, USA) in a buffer: 6 M urea, 200 mM Tris.HCl, pH 9.0, 10 mM EDTA, 0.5% SDS (w/v) and were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 1 h in dark. Labeled proteins were resolved in 8% non-reducing SDS-PAGE and visualized under UV light followed by coomassie staining.</p></sec><sec><title>Promoter activation assay</title><p>A 279 bp region between <italic>whiB</italic>1/Rv3219 start codon and the end of Rv3218 was cloned into the blunt ended site of <italic>Sac</italic>II (upstream to the <italic>lacZ </italic>gene) of the vector pJEM15. The recombinant construct was named <italic>pwhiB1-lacZ</italic>. After confirming the sequence and orientation of the cloned fragment, it was transformed into <italic>M. smegmatis </italic>mc<sup>2</sup>155. Vector alone was used as a control. Three independent clones were inoculated into 20 ml Middlebrook 7H9 medium supplemented with OADC for 24 h (<italic>A</italic><sub>600 </sub>= ~1.8). From this, a fresh medium was inoculated (1%) and grown at 37&#x000b0;C, cells were collected at different time points: 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 days of growth and lysates were prepared. An equal amount of protein in triplicate was assayed for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal activity using Miller's method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. The assay was set in a 96 well plate in a 100 &#x003bc;l reaction volume which had 1 mg/ml protein and 0.8 mg/ml of ONPG dissolved in 'Z buffer': 60 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO4, 40 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO4, (pH 7.0), 10 mM KCl, 1 mM MgSO4 and 2.7 &#x003bc;l/ml <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ME. As yellow color started to appear, the reaction was stopped by adding 50 &#x003bc;l of 1 M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3 </sub>and <italic>A</italic><sub>420 </sub>was measured. The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal activity was calculated in Miller's units by using the formula <italic>A</italic><sub>420</sub>/protein concentration (mg/ml) &#x000d7; time in minutes.</p></sec><sec><title>Miscellaneous</title><p>WhiB1 concentration was estimated using molar extinction coefficient (&#x02208;<sub>280 nm </sub>= 17550 M<sup>-1</sup>cm<sup>-1</sup>). Protein concentration of cell lysate and GlgB was estimated by Bradford's method using BSA as a standard. The nucleotide sequence of all recombinant plasmids were authenticated by sequencing both strands of DNA in an ABI 321 automated DNA sequencer.</p><p>Except in GST pull down assay, throughout the interaction studies, pre-alkylated GlgB was used. Briefly, free cysteines (C<sup>95 </sup>and C<sup>658</sup>) of GlgB were blocked by incubating the protein in 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl and 50 mM IAA for 12 h at 37&#x000b0;C in dark. The unbound IAA was removed by extensive dialysis against buffer: 50 mM Tris.HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AMS: 4-acetamido-4' maleimidyl-stilbene-2: 2'-disulfonic acid; GlgB: &#x003b1;-(1,4)-glucan branching enzyme; <italic>Mtb</italic>: <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>; IAA: iodoacetamide; Trx: thioredoxin; GST: glutathione S-transferase; CNBr: cyanogen bromide; DTT: dithiothreitol; <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-ME: <italic>&#x003b2; </italic>mercaptoethanol</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SKG and MSA carried out all the expression; purification; mutagenesis and biochemical analysis together. KVRK carried out the molecular modeling of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB. RB helped in carrying out some of the biochemical studies. SKG, MSA and PA designed the experiments. MSA and PA together wrote the manuscript. PA oversaw the study. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Figure 1 &#x02013; Characterization of WhiB1 as a bait</bold>. (A) Repression assay to asses the expression and binding of 'bait' to the LexA operator. Four independent transformants of each of the clones were assayed for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal expression. <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>cells (~2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup>) containing constructs (labeled on the x-axis), were permeabilized with 3 drops of chloroform and 2 drops of 0.1% SDS by vigorous vortexing. Reaction was initiated by adding 0.2 ml ONPG (4 mg/ml) in 'Z buffer' for 3.5 minutes at 28&#x000b0;C. The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal activity is expressed as units, on y-axis. (B) WhiB1 lacks intrinsic transcription activity. <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>cells were transformed with pDBD-B1 (bait), pSH18-34 which contains <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal as a reporter gene and library plasmid pJG4-5. The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-gal expression was monitored on the Gal<sup>+</sup>Raff<sup>+</sup>Ura<sup>-</sup>X-gal plate. The panels indicate <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>containing (1) pSH18-34 + pJG4-5 + pDBD-B1, test (2) pSH18-34 + pJG4-5+ pSH17-4, positive control (3) pSH18-34 + pJG4-5 + pRFHM1, negative control. Figure 2 &#x02013; Homology model of <italic>Mtb </italic>GlgB. Three domains are colored differently: N2 domain-orange; TIM-barrel domain-magenta; C-terminal domain-blue. The linker regions between the domains are shown in red. The position of the cysteine residues (C<sup>193</sup>, C<sup>617</sup>and C<sup>658</sup>) on the individual domains is shown as green sticks encircled in dotted boundaries. Figure 3 &#x02013; Over-expression and purification of TrxB/Rv1471 (1) and TrxC/3914 (2) of <italic>Mtb</italic>. The proteins were overexpressed in <italic>E. coli </italic>BL21 (DE3) and were purified by Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA affinity chromatography. Lanes are indicated on the top.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-S1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Table 1 &#x02013; Protein disulfide reductase activity of <italic>Mtb </italic>TrxB and TrxC</bold>. Table 2 &#x02013; List of primers used in this study</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2091-10-1-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>SKG, MSA and RB thank CSIR, India for a Senior Research Fellowship. Sincere thanks to Dr. A. K. Bachhawat for providing the strains and vectors for yeast two-hybrid analysis. Plasmid, pJEM15, was a kind gift from Dr. Brigitte Gicquel, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France. Financial support from DBT and CSIR, Govt. of India is acknowledged. The report is IMTECH communication No. 018/2007.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxin</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1985</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3896121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.54.070185.001321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxin and glutaredoxin systems</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1989</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>13963</fpage><lpage>13966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2668278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxin &#x02013; a fold for all reasons</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1995</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7788290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0969-2126(01)00154-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paget</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttner</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thiol-based regulatory switches</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14616057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genet.37.110801.142538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdbrugger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Droge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze-Osthoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct effects of thioredoxin and antioxidants on the activation of transcription factors NF-kappa B and AP-1</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1672</fpage><lpage>1676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8127864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.5.1672</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidoreductive regulation of nuclear factor kappa B. Involvement of a cellular reducing catalyst thioredoxin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>11380</fpage><lpage>11388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8496188</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosoya-Matsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Motohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisabori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-oxidative stress system in cyanobacteria. Significance of type II peroxiredoxin and the role of 1-Cys peroxiredoxin in <italic>Synechocystis </italic>sp. strain PCC 6803</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>840</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509585</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiglmeier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>CE</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Tekaia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Badcock</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Basham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chillingworth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltwell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornsby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagels</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moule</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajandream</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulston</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deciphering the biology of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>from the complete genome sequence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/31159</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishan</surname><given-names>KVR</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and characterization of &#x003b1;-(1,4)-glucan branching enzyme of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17005418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pep.2006.08.005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes required for mycobacterial growth by high density mutagenesis</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03425.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>KAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three pathways for trehalose biosynthesis in <italic>Mycobacteria</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10658666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cord factor and related trehalose esters</article-title><source>Chem Phys Lipids</source><year>1976</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1269070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0009-3084(76)90001-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besra</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bloom BR</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Lipids and carbohydrates of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title><source>Tuberculosis: Pathogenesis, protection and control</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology, Washington, D. C</publisher-name><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cywes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonopsonic binding of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>to complement receptor type 3 is mediated by capsular polysaccharides and is strain dependent</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1997</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>4258</fpage><lpage>4266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9317035</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor whiB </italic>gene encodes a small transcription factor-like protein dispensable for growth but essential for sporulation</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1316997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00266237</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Eiglmeier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Honor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Basham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chillingworth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Duthoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Feltwell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornsby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagels</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moule</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajandream</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Squares</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Massive gene decay in the leprosy bacillus</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35059006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghunand</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis whmD </italic>and its homologue <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis whiB2 </italic>are functionally equivalent</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>2735</fpage><lpage>2747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16946268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.28911-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>whcE </italic>gene of <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum </italic>is important for survival following heat and oxidative stress</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2005</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.09.115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghunand</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishai</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential gene expression in response to exposure to antimycobacterial agents and other stress conditions among seven <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis whiB</italic>-like genes</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2006</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>2836</fpage><lpage>2841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16870781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00295-06</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Visconti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnappinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Heifets</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoolnik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ancestral antibiotic resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>12200</fpage><lpage>12205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16103351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0505446102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steyn</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hondalus</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>WRJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>WhiB3 interacts with RpoV to affect host survival but is dispensable for <italic>in vivo </italic>growth</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>3147</fpage><lpage>3152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.052705399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guidry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasinhulu</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trombly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Redding</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Steyn</surname><given-names>AJC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>WhiB3 responds to O2 and nitric oxide via its [4Fe-4S] cluster and is essential for nutrient starvation survival</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>11562</fpage><lpage>11567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0700490104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishan</surname><given-names>KVR</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>WhiB1/Rv3219 as a protein disulfide reductase</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2007</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17157031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pep.2006.10.015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular function of WhiB4/Rv3681c of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv: a [4Fe-4S] cluster coordinating protein disulfide reductase</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1414</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17302817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05589.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix-assisted refolding and redox properties of WhiB3/Rv3416 of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2008</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pep.2008.04.010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on structural and functional divergence among seven WhiB proteins of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2009</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19016840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2008.06755.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishitoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobiume</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichijo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian thioredoxin is a direct inhibitor of apoptosis signal-regulating kinase (ASK) 1</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2596</fpage><lpage>2606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9564042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.9.2596</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishitoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichijo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyriakis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of Apoptosis Signal-Regulating Kinase 1 (ASK1) by Tumor Necrosis Factor Receptor-Associated Factor 2 Requires Prior Dissociation of the ASK1 Inhibitor Thioredoxin</article-title><source>Mol and Cell Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2198</fpage><lpage>2208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.20.6.2198-2208.2000</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhandayuthapani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of anti-sigma factor antagonists of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis </italic>in the yeast two-hybrid system</article-title><source>Tuberculosis (Edinb)</source><year>2005</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16263329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2005.08.001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Leggio</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and crystallization of an active N-terminally truncated form of the <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>glycogen branching enzyme</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>2150</fpage><lpage>2155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10759837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-1327.2000.01221.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abad</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Binderup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios-Steiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arni</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The X-ray crystallographic structure of <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>branching enzyme</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>42164</fpage><lpage>42170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M205746200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binderup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Truncation of the amino terminus of branching enzyme changes its chain transfer pattern</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>2002</year><volume>397</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11795883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abbi.2001.2544</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leggio</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A structural model for the N-terminal N1 module of <italic>E. coli </italic>glycogen branching enzyme</article-title><source>Biologia Bratislava</source><year>2002</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpp</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hisabori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive survey of proteins targeted by chloroplast thioredoxin</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>11224</fpage><lpage>11229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11553771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.191282098</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaskitt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue-specific glycogen branching isoenzymes in a multicellular prokaryote, <italic>Streptomyces coelicolor </italic>A3(2)</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8596463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1995.mmi_18010089.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gicquel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic>-mycobacteria shuttle vectors for operon and gene fusions to lacZ: the pJEM series</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>6749</fpage><lpage>6753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7961429</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Florencio</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxin-linked processes in cyanobacteria are as numerous as in chloroplasts, but targets are different</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>16107</fpage><lpage>16112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14673118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2534397100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli </italic>thioredoxin stabilizes complexes of bacteriophage T7 DNA polymerase and primed templates</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1987</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>16224</fpage><lpage>16232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3316215</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishitoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobiume</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichijo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian thioredoxin is a direct inhibitor of apoptosis signal-regulating kinase (ASK) 1</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2596</fpage><lpage>2606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9564042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.9.2596</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular cloning: A laboratory manual</source><year>2001</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold spring Harbor, New York</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Solanki</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fingerprinting method for phylogenetic classification and identification of microorganisms based on variation in 16S rRNA gene sequences</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>2000</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10907085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golemis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paul L</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Searching for interacting proteins with the two-hybrid system III. The Two-Hybrid Screen</article-title><source>Bartel and Stanley Fields</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Experiments in Molecular Genetics</source><year>1972</year><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. Cold Spring Harbor, New York</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


